<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The clergies honour: or, the lives of St. Basil the Great, Archbishop of Neo-cæsarea, and St. Chrysostom, Archbishop of Constantinople. Drawn by way of parallel</title>
            <author>Dowell, John, ca. 1627-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81687</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2055C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223910</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897570</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897570</idno>
            <idno type="VID">132826</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81687)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 132826)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2513:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The clergies honour: or, the lives of St. Basil the Great, Archbishop of Neo-cæsarea, and St. Chrysostom, Archbishop of Constantinople. Drawn by way of parallel</title>
                  <author>Dowell, John, ca. 1627-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 94, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Nat. Thompson, for William Cooper, at the Pelican in Little-Britain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>John Chrysostom, --  Saint, d. 407 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Basil, --  Saint, Bishop of Caesarea, ca. 329-379 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:132826:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132826:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Clergies Honour:</hi> OR, THE LIVES OF St. <hi>BASIL</hi> the Great, Archbiſhop of <hi>Neo-caeſarea,</hi> AND St. <hi>CHRYSOSTOM,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> Drawn by way of Parallel.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>A Biſhop then muſt be blameleſs.</p>
               <bibl>1 Tim. 3. 2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>Chryſ. in Epiſt. 1 Tim.</bibl>
               <p>'Tis neceſſary for him, who governs the Church, to ſhine more illuſtriouſly then the brighteſt Lamp; in his Converſation the leaſt ſpot muſt not appear: The Splendor of his Vertues, and Graces, muſt draw the eyes of all perſons to him, and ſweetly enforce them to conform their actions according to the pattern of his more elevated demeanour.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nat. Thompſon,</hi> for <hi>William Cooper,</hi> at the <hi>Pelican</hi> in <hi>Little-Britain,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:132826:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:132826:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT cannot be otherwiſe imagined, but when a contempt is caſt upon Religion, a ſcorn muſt be thrown upon thoſe who adminiſter Holy Offices: nay when God himſelf is blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed, can any admire, that thoſe who wait at his Altar, ſhould lie under the greateſt ſlight, and ſuffer under the ſeverest reproaches? If they call the Maſter of the houſe <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> how much more them of the houſhold! no Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant can be civilly received, when his Maſter is ſcorned. I have endeavoured to vindicate the glory of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in the Treatiſe called, <hi>The Triumph of Chriſtianity.</hi> I ſtile this, <hi>The Clergies Honour,</hi> by giving the Lives of two excellent <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers: I entitle it a <hi>Parallel.</hi> I have given an account of both their Grandeurs, and as God hath distributed to ſeveral perſons various Gifts, ſo have I given my conjecture in what one excelled the other. I preſent unto the Reader in a Collation, both theſe from their Cradles to their Graves. I call them Archbiſhops; they both commanded
<pb facs="tcp:132826:3"/> other Biſhops, which is clearly manifeſted by St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Journey into <hi>Aſia,</hi> in which he depoſed ſeveral Biſhops; and St. <hi>Baſil</hi>'s Letter to thoſe Biſhops in <hi>Pontus,</hi> who had Simoniacally taken money for Ordination, in which he alone Excommunicated them. The name <hi>Patriarch,</hi> taken from the <hi>Jews,</hi> was not known till after-times. The ſcorn which is caſt upon the Clergy, is every where ſufficiently no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, which this Pen ſhall take no notice of. I ſhall make ſome ſhort reflections upon ſome paſſages which have come from the Preſs. The Prefacer to Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> his Book of Neceſſity, thus ſaith: <hi>If we conſider the practices of thoſe who pretend to be the Interpreters of them,</hi> (i. e.) <hi>the Scriptures, and to make them fit meat for the people, how that inſtead of renouncing the World, they endeavour to raiſe themſelves in the greateſt Promotions, leiſure and luxury, that they make them the decoys of the People, to carry on Deſigns and Intrigues of State, and ſtudy the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this World, more then any other people, he will find ſome grounds to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the practiſe of ſuch to be the greateſt diſturbance, burden and vexation of the Chriſtian part of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a calumny as falſe as odious: 'tis too
<pb facs="tcp:132826:3"/> ſadly to be bewail'd, that there are amongst the Clergy many guilty of thoſe crimes; but muſt the Vices of ſome be charged upon the Body of the Clergy? Did theſe Fathers ſcrew themſelves into Preferment? No; they were deſervedly advanced into great Dignities in the Church, yet theſe Honours they declined as long as they could. Into Eaſe? No; they were the moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious perſons in the World. Into Luxuries? No; they were perſons who lived in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of a prodigious Mortification, and Auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Into Riches? No; the Estates left by their Parents, and gain'd in their Eccleſiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Dignities, they ſpent upon the Poor; that when they died, they might juſtly with St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> when he was dying, ſay, <hi>Pauper Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianus non habet unde condat Teſtamentum.</hi> The ſame may be truly averred of thouſands more almoſt in all Ages of the Church, who flouriſh'd in all vertue and goodneſs, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Chriſtianity amiable by the admirableneſs of their lives; and by the lustre of their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and purity of Doctrine, attracted many from a ſtate of Impiety, into a ſweet compliance with Religion, and the practice of all good. Mr. <hi>Dryden,</hi> a Poet of no mean parts and learning, whoſe Fancy is fully agreeing with a ſoft humour, ſpares not <hi>Cowley,</hi> the glory of his
<pb facs="tcp:132826:4"/> age, who lies wrapt up in his immortal ſheets: He will not ſuffer the Clergy to paſs without a laſh; thus ſaith he, <hi>Separated Beings may be better explicated by Poets, then by Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers or Divines; for ſpeculations on theſe are Poetical, Fancy being in Poets ſharper then in dull and heavy Gown-men.</hi> There are Gown-men in the World neither heavy nor dull; Fancy in an excellent Divine, is as high as in any Poet: Eloquence is the product of Fancy and Imagination, which takes as great a flight in Divines, as in any perſons of the World. The Judgment and Learning of Dr. <hi>Beaumont,</hi> the preſent <hi>Regius Profeſſor</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> is known to the World; this may cauſe Mr. <hi>Dryden</hi> to rank him among the number of the dull and heavy Gown-men: but ſurely Mr. <hi>Dryden</hi> will think the Fancy of that great man equals his own. But why muſt the ſpeculation of ſeparated Beings be the act of Fancy? indeed if with Mr. <hi>Hobbs</hi> he thinks that Spirits, and incorporeal ſubstances, imply a contradiction, that Miracles are as Castles raiſed in the Air, there might be ſome pretence; yet were there no real Spirits and incorporeal ſubſtances, it were an unjust aſſertion: for the ſpeculation of the nature of ſeparated Beings, is the act of the Judgment, and not Fancy, and
<pb facs="tcp:132826:4"/> thereby not Poetical; it belongs not to Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but Reaſon, that is light and airy, this ponderous and grave Imagination which makes a Poet conform the nature of things to its own Idea; but Judgment beſides Eloquence being neceſſary for a Divine and Philoſopher, brings its own Idea to the nature of the things. If Mr. <hi>Dryden</hi> be appeal'd, can it be credited that he will affirm Fancy to be the judge of the nature of things? There is a Gentleman who hath wrote a Tract, ſtiled, <hi>Reflections upon the Eloquence of the Bar and Pulpit,</hi> who hath ſeverely cenſured the <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers. Thus ſaith he: <hi>The order, their deſign, the matter they treat on, are very little juſt, and not conformable to precepts of Art.</hi> He gives a ſtrange and bold character of the most eloquent perſons of the World. That Gentleman, if ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the <hi>Greek</hi> Fathers, did not ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that moſt of their Sermons were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to posterity, by the care of Sermon-writers, <hi>Brachygraphy</hi> being much uſed at <hi>Rome</hi> and in <hi>Greece.</hi> There is a vast diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Sermons reviſed by the Authors, and thoſe which are publiſhed by the care of <hi>Brachygraphers.</hi> I must averr, that thoſe Tracts which the two <hi>Gregories,</hi> St. <hi>Baſil</hi> and St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> wrote and corrected, for their
<pb facs="tcp:132826:5"/> elegancy of ſtile, quickneſs of conceit, exactneſs of order, braveneſs of matter, power of forcing the mind, are inferiour to ſew or none of the moſt corrected pieces of the Eaſt. From the Pens of excellent perſons ſomething falls rude and unpolite, yet in their careleſs <hi>Opera</hi>'s there will be ſeen the lineaments of a noble Wit, and Judgment. The like may be ſaid of the meaneſt Tracts of theſe great perſons, which totally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves that raſh character. 'Tis no wonder that <hi>Spinoſa</hi> ſhould ſhew himſelf ſo declared an enemy to Chriſtianity, when he reproaches all ſorts of Religions, and Humane Nature it ſelf. Concerning Mankind thus ſaith he; <note place="margin">Sp. Trac. Theol. pol. cap. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Men are born to devour Men, as greater Fiſhes the leſs:</hi> which words carry in them as great a ſcorn and debaſement to Mankind, as can be imagined. To expoſe Christianity he uſes theſe words: <hi>I have</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Praefat.</note> 
               <hi>often wondred that men who glory, that they are Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, that they have entertained that Religion, which commands love, ſweetneſs of ſociety, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of behaviour, juſtice, and faith to all; ſhould ſo bitterly contend amongſt themſelves, and proſecute one another with implacable hatred; that the Articles of Faith, which each party confeſſes, may
<pb facs="tcp:132826:5"/> ſooner be known by a contrary, then by their own Faction; and to caſt an ignominy upon all Religion, things are thus reduced; none can be diſcerned, whether he be a Chriſtian, a Turk, a Jew, or Heathen, but by his garb and mean, that he frequents that Church, has embraced this or that Opinion, and is the follower of ſome, whom he calls Maſter; otherwiſe there is the ſame manner of life to all; theſe things being waved, the Profeſſors of different Forms agree in the ſame converſation.</hi> Theſe imputations are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true and invidious. Religion is in it ſelf not leſs excellent, becauſe the Profeſſors of it are bad; let all men be liars, God is true. The wicked lives of men, derogate not from the glory of Religion; the intemperance of moſt men, do not ſully the ſplendour of temperance. If Miniſters of State, Judges, and Officers at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending the Law, do by bribery and delay, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, craft, or any evil means, injure the People; their ill adminiſtration of Juſtice, doth not diminiſh the reaſon and goodneſs of Laws. and there is certainly nothing more evident then this, that no perſons in the World have lived lives ſo full of reaſon and goodneſs, as Chriſtians have done; none ſo manifeſted ſo ardent a love and affection to their Lord and
<pb facs="tcp:132826:6"/> Maſter, and to one another, as they have: and this is certainly true, that as the genius of Chriſtian Religion tends to peace, to univerſal charity, and to all ſorts of vertues; ſo than Christians, none more illustriouſly practiſed them, nor ſuffered more in the exerciſe of them. Let any one take a view of the Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and many millions of others; can they be charged with Luxury, with Pride, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Covetouſneſs, Cruelty? No; but on the other ſide, in them were eminent a rigorous Abſtinence, a profound Humility, a generous contempt of this World, an aſſiduous labour, the ſweeteſt affection towards their Brethren, a peaceable diſpoſition, a moſt intenſe endeavour to make all men truly happy. But what means that falſe obloquy of <hi>Spinoſa, Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion does teach Concord and Love,</hi> &amp;c. Though in too many the contrary Vices were too manifeſt, yet it is equally certain in many others, thoſe admirable Vertues were gloriouſly elucent. When he urges againſt Religion, <hi>ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting aſide the frequenting of ſome Church, and all ſorts of perſons, agree in the ſame manner of life;</hi> what ſence does that bear other than this? All ſorts of perſons eat and drink; in all ſorts of Profeſſions there are active and contemplative men; they exerciſe
<pb facs="tcp:132826:6"/> all ſorts of Arts and Sciences; but what then? cannot there be ſufficient marks or evidences given, of what Religion a perſon is of, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the truth of Chriſtianity? The Profeſſors of it acknowledge <hi>Jeſus</hi> to be the Son of God, that he came into the World to give us ſuch Laws, and upon condition of Obedience pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſuch a happineſs and reward; what though they eat and drink, be imployed in Arts and Trades, cannot they give evident teſtimonies of being genuine Christians? If that they regulate their eating and drinking, the management of their Trades and Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, according to the Laws that their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter preſcribed them; entertain the Principles of Faith, and are guided by the Commands that he hath given them; are ready to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt their affection to their Lord, by dying in the defence of his Faith, and for his honour; how can they give greater evidence of their being his genuine Diſciples? That the Clergy have endeavoured to make great Places and Preferments to be the Inſtruments of Vice, is not to be denied, but moſt ſadly to be bewailed: but that abundance of the Chriſtian Clergy, and thoſe of ſuch a Profeſſion, were ſuperiour to any of the like in any condition in the World, and have outvied them in the ſplendor
<pb facs="tcp:132826:7"/> of moſt excellent actions, is with equal truth to be aſſerted. The World has not produced better perſons, then what the Church has: In all Profeſſions, as in the ſtate of man, there are various degrees, and diverſities of condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; but in this, the Church may juſtly glory, that multitudes of her Clergy have ſlighted all the invitations to Honour, Riches or Eaſe; and that abundance of them, who have been compelled to accept of Honours and Eſtates, have by their carriages demonſtrated, that in the affluence of Riches, Charity and Poverty of Spirit to be the greateſt treaſures; and in the accumulation of Honours, Humility to be their greatest glory. And it is indubitable, that the Arguments and Reaſons which the enemies of our glorious Religion uſe againſt it, are falſe and frivolous, the Principles of their Philoſophy are abſurd and full of contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that they place their ſurest refuge in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies and Slanders; it behoves all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to ſtudy the honour of their profeſſion, to promote peace, to advance ſanctity, and ſtop the mouths of all gainſayers, that <hi>Sion</hi> may be the praiſe of the whole Earth, her Stones may be laid with Saphirs, and her foundation with fair Colours.</p>
            <p>Theſe glorious Propheſies, which have not
<pb facs="tcp:132826:7"/> yet been accompliſhed, will certainly be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. When the beauty of the houſe of the Lord openly appears, then the honour of them that administer Holy Offices, will not be obſcured. That Earl, great for his vast Wit, rendred ignoble by his Crimes, through the grace of God made illuſtrious by his remarkable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, in the career of his Impieties, cast a ſcorn upon the Clergy; being enlightned by the Rays of Heaven, acknowledged <hi>how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily heretofore he had treated that Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of men, reproaching them that they were proud, and propheſied only for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; but now he had learnt how to value them: That he eſteemed them the Servants of the moſt High God, who were to ſhew to him the way to Everlaſting Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reproaches cast upon thoſe, who wait up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Altar, are not to be attributed to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or the Doctrine, which they are engaged to preach. There is a vast difference between the product of vicious paſſions, and evil habits: We do juſtly reproach our Adverſaries with this great wickedneſs, that by an immediate conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence from their Sentiments, no worſhip can be given to the ever-glorious and Eternal God, no obedience or faithful ſubjection to the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magistrate, no juſtice between man and
<pb facs="tcp:132826:8"/> man. The ſame great perſon thus laments: <hi>The abſurd and fooliſh Philoſophy, which the World ſo much admired, propagated by the late Mr.</hi> Hobbs, <hi>and others, had undone him and many more of the beſt Parts in the Nation.</hi> The wickedneſs of our Opponents can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not charge the Commandments of the bleſſed <hi>Jeſus</hi> with the least errour. For the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and flouriſhing of Chriſtianity, we will put up our prayers to Almighty God, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing may ſeparate us from the love of God, which is in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Ordain, O Lord, a Lamp for thine anointed; deck thy Prieſts with Salvation, and make thy Saints ſing aloud for joy. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authorities">
            <pb facs="tcp:132826:8"/>
            <p>THe Compiler of this Tract hath not given the particular account of each Author, out of which he hath collected this Hiſtory; but he aſſures the Reader, that he Traded not with any fabulous Writer: he durſt not truſt <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s Biographers, but the Books out of which he hath taken this Parallel, are,</p>
            <list>
               <item>St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> Graecè: Ed. Froben: Baſileae 1551:</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> Graecè: Ed. Herbagi: Baſileae 1550.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> Graecè: Ed. Savilianâ: Aetonae 1612.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Socrates, Sozomen, Theodoret,</hi> Graecè: Ed. Steph. Pariſ. 1544.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Photii Bibliotheca,</hi> Gr. &amp; Lat. Ed. Rothom. 1653.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 11. lin. 6. dele <hi>the Snow of,</hi> p. 17. l. 26. ſet the colon point after <hi>Grave,</hi> p. 63. in the marg. for <hi>Appeals,</hi> read <hi>Fraternal Addreſſes,</hi> p. 64. l. 27. <hi>when the Eaſt was ſo dreadfully tormented,</hi> are a Parentheſis, l. 29. r. <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and dele the comma.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:132826:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:132826:9"/>
            <head>The PARALLEL Of the LIVES of St. <hi>Baſil</hi> the Great, AND St. <hi>John Chryſoſtom.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>HElenopontus,</hi> a mean City of the <note place="margin">The Birth and Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of St. <hi>Baſil.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cappadocian Pontus,</hi> had for ever been obſcured in the Charts of Geographers, had not the Birth of <hi>Baſilius</hi> given it a perpetual luſtre; whoſe Parents were of ancient and great Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. His Grandfather was one of the Nobles of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> and made more Honourable by the Chriſtianity which he gloriouſly profeſſed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Maximinian</hi> Perſecution occaſioned his flight into the Deſarts of <hi>Pontus;</hi> whither he, with ſome brave perſons, his Friends, and ſome of his Family, retired; and there for ſeven years he lived: That wild Deſart afforded no other meat than what his Prayers obtained from Heaven, the Beaſts and the Fowls that fed him, were Priſoners of his prayers, they being caught by no other Snares or Nets, than thoſe his Ejaculations had prepared. Yet ſuppoſing men might afford a greater liberty, and ſhew a more fair civility, than
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:132826:10"/> the Beaſts of the <hi>Pontick</hi> Wilderneſs, he ventured again into the open Air of <hi>Cappadocia;</hi> where, though his expectation was cheated, his Faith was permanent; and what the ſavage Beaſts did not act, the devilliſh Pagans perpetrated; by whom he received a cruel, but glorious death; the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals of the Church perpetuating the day of his Martyrdom.</p>
            <p>The Parents of <hi>Baſil</hi> were <hi>Baſilius</hi> and <hi>Emme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia: Baſilius</hi> his Sanctity advanced him to an Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Dignity, which he managed with great piety and prudence. <hi>Emmelia</hi> ſurvived her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band many years, who had the unuſual felicity of the proſperous holineſs of ten Children, (five of whom were Sons, three of which were Biſhops of eminent wit and holineſs) the glory of that preſent and ſucceeding Ages. At her death, which happen'd in the 90<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> year of her age, <hi>Macrina</hi> her eldeſt Daughter, and <hi>Peter</hi> her youngeſt Son were preſent; before they cloſed her eyes, that heavenly Widow laid her hands upon her eldeſt Child, which was <hi>Macrina,</hi> and on <hi>Peter,</hi> then a Presbyter, her youngeſt Child, and gave up the Ghoſt with theſe heavenly paſſages: <hi>O my Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God, in this my eldest Daughter, and this my youngest Son, I dedicate my whole harveſt of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to thy Divine Majesty; and in theſe prayers I commend my Soul unto thee; the firſt fruits and tenths are thine; all, O my God, are thine, into thy hands I commit my Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of ſuch a Father, and ſuch a Mother the great <hi>Baſilius</hi> was born, <hi>Anno</hi> 319. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> being the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:132826:10"/> fifth, and <hi>Licinianus</hi> the firſt time Conſuls. O glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious felicity! an aged Lady living in ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Piety, ſeeing her Children to be the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the Church, and glory of their Age, thus happily in the vigour of her parts and piety to breath out her bleſſed Soul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antioch,</hi> the Metropolis of <hi>Syria,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives an eternal honour by the Birth <note place="margin">Of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> which happen'd <hi>Anno</hi> 354 <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the ſeventh, and <hi>Gallus</hi> the third time Conſuls. His Parents, <hi>Secundus</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſa,</hi> were of the Noble Race of the Senators of <hi>Antioch. Mileſius</hi> the Archbiſhop of that See, was the inſtrument of converting them from Paganiſm to Chriſtianity. His Father <hi>Secundus</hi> died, when <hi>Anthuſa</hi> his Mother was but 20 years of age; who after the deceaſe of her Husband, lived in a perpetual Widowhood. <hi>Secundus</hi> was unwilling to ſurvive that glorious honour which Chriſtianity had conferred on him, fearing he might defile the white Garments of his Baptiſm, with a ſubſequent viciouſneſs. She to manifeſt that entire love, which Chriſtianity had encreaſed in her purer breaſt, to her Husband, gained that honour from the Enemies of Chriſtianity, that <hi>Libanius</hi> the Pagan, yet Eloquent Orator of <hi>Antioch,</hi> enquiring of <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> himſelf the age of his Mother, <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> anſwered, 40 years; and again asking what ſtate of life ſhe embraced, he return'd, Widowhood, which ſhe had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued for 20 years: (for his Father <hi>Secundus</hi> died when his Mother was but 20 years old) at which
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:132826:11"/> reply he cryed with a ſtrange joy and aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his Auditors and Pupils, <hi>See, what famous Women are amongst Christians!</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to that profuſe Gentleman, who upbraided him with the meanneſs of his Parentage, ſmartly replied, <hi>I give a lustre to my Family, but you have obſcured the glory of your Ancestors.</hi> Of theſe great Perſons the queſtion will not eaſily be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, whether from their Parents they received, or unto them gave the greater Splendor: But it is unqueſtionably true, that no Parents had Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of greater Excellencies, nor Children had Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of higher Accompliſhments. Theſe perſons of ſingular extraction, remembred the Nobility of their birth, and would do nothing unworthy of ſo great a deſcent. As <hi>China</hi> Diſhes receive their perfection from a long continuance in the Earth, and thereby are prepar'd for ornament and moſt excellent uſes; ſo Nobility dignified by a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſucceſſion, is fitted for the gallanteſt imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the greateſt actions. Happy certainly were thoſe Ages of the Church, when Nobles offer'd themſelves up willingly to ſerve the Lord; when a Chair of State was not more valued, than an Epiſcopal See. <hi>Plato</hi> rejoyced in the happineſs of thoſe Commonwealths, who had Philoſophers for their Princes: and certainly it would be a great felicity and ſplendor to the Church, if the Nobility were her Prelates and Governours. The Revenues and Dignity of the Church generally came from the Nobility, who diveſted themſelves to cloath the Altar; and there is nothing more
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:132826:11"/> reaſonable, than that the Church ſhould confer her Honours on thoſe perſons, to whom ſhe is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſil</hi> having the great happineſs of a <note place="margin">The Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of <hi>Baſil.</hi>
               </note> Noble man, and a learned Biſhop to his Father, he needed for his younger years no other School than the Biſhops; where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the firſt Rudiments of Grammar and Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, with the accompliſhments of Sanctified and Gentile manners in his Education: In him Holineſs and Civility ſweetly met, both of which received a luſtre by a learned inſtitution. To ripen his great parts, and to furniſh him with the univerſal Literature, and the comprehenſive knowledge of Men and Books, he was ſent firſt to <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> the Metropolis of <hi>Cappadocia;</hi> thence to <hi>Constantinople,</hi> flouriſhing then with a conflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the greateſt Wits in the World: 'twas then the Reſidence of the Emperors of the Weſt; from thence he travelled into <hi>Athens,</hi> where he was firſt acquainted with the great <hi>Nazianzen. Athens</hi> as yet continued to be the common Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy of the World, where was the greateſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the moſt Eloquent perſons of that Age. And as amongſt the <hi>Greeks</hi> in former times, none was eſteemed for a brave Combatant, unleſs he had been victorious in the <hi>Olympick</hi> Games; ſo none was reputed a great Philoſopher or Orator, who in the Schools of <hi>Athens</hi> had not received the Acclamations of Victory and Triumph. He was then but about one and thirty years of age: his fame flew to <hi>Athens</hi> before he could there ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:132826:12"/> and was ſufficiently known The repute of his Learning was ſo great, that it freed him from that toyiſh Rite and ridiculous Ceremony uſed in the Matriculation of young Scholars into that Academy. That pretty Ridicule, mixed with ſomething ſerious, was after this manner: The New-comer was firſt amicably entertained, and received in the houſe of ſome of his Friends, or by one or other of the Maſters of Oratory: After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he is aſſaulted with perpetual Jeers, ſome impudently taunt him, others more learnedly abuſe him; this Stranger as his manners are Clowniſh or Gentile, Sottiſh or Ingenuous, is vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly treated; yet is ſufficiently abuſed by the Wits of the Academy, which ſeems very barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to thoſe that are ignorant of the Rites, but to thoſe that know it, it's pleaſant and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and the end of this Tragedy is the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of mirth and laughter to the Wits of the Town, who entertained themſelves with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the ingenious abuſes put upon this No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and the uncouth replies given by him: And afterwards in State through the Market-place he is carried to a Bath, the young Academicks going in order two and two before him; when coming near to the Bath, they give a fearful ſhout, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and antickly skipping as Enthuſiaſts; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending they might not be admitted to the Bath, but by their vehement knocking, and loud out-cries, they terrifie the young Scholar, the doors are opened, he's admitted into the Bath, and coming out he is received as a member of their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:132826:12"/> Univerſity, their Friend, and Companion. From this Pageantry, the Learning of <hi>Baſil</hi> exempted him; who in the Schools was aſſaulted by two <hi>Armenian</hi> Orators, men of great Wits, but of greater Impudence, whom he forced out of the Schools to their eternal diſhonour. From thence he went to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> afterwards to <hi>Antioch,</hi> where he converſed with as great <hi>Orators</hi> as the World afforded. At <hi>Athens</hi> he was taught the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of Eloquence, by thoſe famous Rhetori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians <hi>Hymerius</hi> and <hi>Proareſius:</hi> his fellow Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats were <hi>Nazianzen, Julian</hi> and <hi>Libanius,</hi> all of great Eloquence and Learning. Fifteen years he ſpent in travelling unto, and reſiding in the beſt Schools and Academies of the World; whereby he attained a vaſt knowledge in Philoſophy, Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, and all humane Literature. What indeed could not be attained by ſo great a Wit, enjoying ſo gallant an Education!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> being born at <hi>Antioch,</hi> then the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>Syria,</hi> and the third <hi>Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archal</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Of <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>See,</hi> flouriſhing with Riches and Arts. The greateſt <hi>Orators</hi> and <hi>Philoſophers</hi> of the age there opened the Schools under <hi>Andragathius:</hi> He was inſtructed in the various Sciences of <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy</hi> under <hi>Libanius,</hi> the Eloquenteſt man of that age; his natural propenſity and fitneſs for <hi>Oratory,</hi> ripened into the higheſt perfection that ever the Pews of <hi>Pagans,</hi> or the Pulpits of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> knew. The Admiration that <hi>Libanius</hi> had of him, engag'd all the <hi>Orators</hi> of that time to love the Sweetneſs of his tongue, and fear the greatneſs of his parts.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:132826:13"/> 
               <hi>Libanius</hi> his Maſter ſtood in awe of his Scholars Cenſure. Though he needed not the travels of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil,</hi> by reaſon of thoſe great Advantages which <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi> abounded with above <hi>Helenopontus;</hi> yet for Curioſity ſake, rather then for Neceſſity, to teach, rather then to be taught, he travelled to <hi>Athens;</hi> where being admitted to pronounce an Oration before the <hi>Senate,</hi> he was by their Decree and Suffrage declared to be Superiour in Eloquence to <hi>Anthemius,</hi> the moſt Renowned Orator of that Academy.</p>
            <p>The Divine Grace, who prompted <hi>Baſil</hi> in his Study and Travels, fitted him for brave underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings. <hi>Heaven</hi> ſo prevailed upon his mind, that he deſigned to ſpend the remainder of his Life in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Eccleſiaſtical Imployments. His Travel to <hi>Alexandria</hi> gave him an acquaintance with the Religious perſons of <hi>Egypt;</hi> where an <hi>Aſcetick</hi> life moſt gloriouſly flouriſhed. The Inſtructers in an holy and divine life were the moſt admired Fathers of <hi>Egypt,</hi> who inflam'd his breaſt, hugely diſpoſed to piety, with thoſe divine <hi>ardors,</hi> which preſently conſumed in him all divine affections and inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; ſo that without intermingling with any Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil affairs, he retired for the enjoyment of God by Prayer, Study and Meditation, into Solitude.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> whoſe prodigious Eloquence <note place="margin">Of <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi>
               </note> ſomewhat ballanced his divine Soul, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined that he might ſerve the Eternal God by the defence of oppreſſed perſons. He therefore reſolved upon ſo excellent an intent to improve his Parts and Learning, to betake himſelf to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:132826:13"/> Pleadings and Orations: But experience taught him, that the trouble and diverſions impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his progreſs in a more Heavenly life. He there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forſook that imployment, and retired into the Deſarts of <hi>Syria;</hi> and under the conduct of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> and <hi>Carterius,</hi> he was inſtructed in that life which he moſt deſired, to wit, in imitating the life of <hi>Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſilius</hi> prepared for Eccleſiaſtical af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baſils</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment.</note> which he totally deſigned: he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through all Eccleſiaſtical Orders. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py perſons who are fitted for the Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before they undertake it. They ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom fail of any buſineſs, who enter upon it with the greateſt conſideration. It is the Frenzy to poliſh the ſtones in the building, after they are laid upon the foundation. The late Author of the Contempt of the <hi>Clergy</hi> is hugely miſtaken, when he attributes it to their Poverty: for Poverty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſes no man that is virtuous, nor do Riches ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt any perſon that is vitious. 'Tis ſanctity that is the glory of the Clergy: This is the grand mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, that they muſt be made fit for the Miniſtry after they have entred into Orders. He firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a <hi>Reader,</hi> then order'd <hi>Deacon,</hi> afterwards was made <hi>Priest</hi> of <hi>Caeſarea. Chryſoſtom,</hi> after he had ſpent three years in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> by reaſon of a violent Sickneſs, returns to <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och;</hi> where he entred into Sacred Orders, and from the loweſt degree of a <hi>Reader,</hi> he aſcended to the <hi>Archiepiſcopal See</hi> of <hi>Constantinople.</hi> They build the higheſt, who lay the ſureſt foundation in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:132826:14"/> Humility: So great an honour was given to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that the greateſt wits diſdained not to be <hi>Readers</hi> in the Church of God. The beſt of <hi>Kings,</hi> of whom our Lord and Saviour was deſcended, though he changed his <hi>Shepherds</hi> Crook into an Imperial Crown, yet he preferred the being a Door-keeper in the Houſe of the Lord, to the dwelling in the <hi>Tents</hi> of wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>In the Judgment of <hi>Photius,</hi> the greateſt <hi>Critick</hi> in the World, the ſtiles of both <note place="margin">The ſtiles of <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom.</hi>
               </note> of them were not exceeded by <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> in Purity, Significancy and Propriety. The Greatneſs of their minds manifeſted themſelves in the Majeſty of their Pens, and Tongues the conſtancy in their even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <hi>Baſil</hi> had very few Excurſions; the more frequent Digreſſions of <hi>Chryſostom</hi> wanted not their uſual ſweetneſs and Eloquence, or juſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. A <hi>Virgin</hi> modeſty always appeared in their Writings, flowing from the purity of their Souls. They were full of Humility; their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage never ſavoured of affectation. There are no <hi>Monuments</hi> in which the Eloquency, <hi>Copiouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Majesty</hi> of the <hi>Greek</hi> language are more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous, then in the Writings of theſe Great <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. Baſil</hi> did more convince, <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade; <hi>Baſil</hi> had more of the Courtier, <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostom</hi> was more Popular; <hi>Baſil</hi> more of a <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, Chryſoſtom</hi> of an <hi>Orator: Baſil</hi> a better Diſputant, <hi>Chryſostom</hi> the more affectionate <hi>Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher; Baſil</hi> like a clear yet deep River, whoſe Majeſtick motions admit of no impediments;
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:132826:14"/> 
               <hi>Chryſostom</hi> like a rapid, yet pure ſtream, that ſweeps all things before it. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> could car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Peoples affections as he pleaſed, he could hurry his Auditors by the violence of his <hi>Oratory</hi> into any Paſſion; Now he could draw tears from hearts as cruel as <hi>Tygers</hi> bred in the Snow of <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſus,</hi> again he could inſpire the breaſts of thoſe whoſe Spirits were as mean as the timerous <hi>Hare,</hi> with zeal and courage. <hi>Baſil</hi> commanded in all his <hi>Auditors</hi> ſo great a reſpect, that when he was in the Church his <hi>Auditors</hi> ſtood as living <hi>Statues</hi> filled with Admiration and Reverence, which his great Reaſon and Holineſs, mixt with a profound Eloquence, had raiſed in them.</p>
            <p>Both of them were of an invincible <note place="margin">The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> and <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom.</hi>
               </note> Courage, and Adamantine Conſtancy; they could not be molified with Pleaſures, Terrours could not affright them. Their Temperance was ſo exceſſive, that their whole lives were a continued faſt; they eat but once a day; they contemned the <hi>World,</hi> as though they were <hi>Angels</hi> upon <hi>Earth;</hi> They, who would not yield to the fury of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors, or the rage of Hereticks, yet were tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed towards their Enemies, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſhelter them from any Popular fury; They were of a vaſt charity, their Eſtate might, but their Mind could not admit of any bounds of Liberality; They were indefatigable in Labour, as the <hi>Heavenly Orbs,</hi> and were conſtantly in motion, their Prayers conſtant, their Sermons frequent, they indulged no further the Neceſſities
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:132826:15"/> of Nature, then as they might be ſubſervient to Religion; and no buſineſs did they admit of, but what promoted Piety. Thus they ſeemed as the <hi>Birds</hi> of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> who though they exerciſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a continual flight, live only upon the dew of <hi>Heaven.</hi> As in the building of a Temple there are ſeveral materials of various qualities, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the Erecting of that Structure, yet all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to the beauty and form of the Edifice; So in <hi>Baſil</hi> we find more Lenity and Sweetneſs, in <hi>Chryſostom</hi> more Fervour and Auſterity; in <hi>Baſil</hi> more Prudence, in <hi>Chryſostom</hi> a greater Violence; <hi>Baſil</hi> the Wiſer man, <hi>Chryſostom</hi> the more impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly Couragious; <hi>Baſil</hi> diſpoſed to win Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by the Charms of love, and conſume them by no other fire, then that of kindneſs and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Baſil</hi> when he reflected with Anger upon the Vices, carried a reſpect to the Perſons; <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> ſeems ſo tranſported againſt all ſin, that he took no conſideration of the Perſons that offended, yet the ſweetneſs of the one, and the ſeverity of the other, the Courage and Piety of both give a perpetual Luſtre to the Church of God. As choice Fruits that are ſooneſt ripen'd with the greater fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of the <hi>Sun,</hi> loſe nothing of their Beauty and native Excellence; So <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> having the vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his parts elevated by the peculiar influence of the Grace of God, at two and twenty years of age ſet forth the Eternal <hi>Monuments</hi> of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> the three books of <hi>Prieſthood;</hi> and by then he was twenty eight years of age, had made theſe Excellent <hi>Sermons,</hi> which to his Eternal Honour are
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:132826:15"/> yet extant againſt <hi>Jews, Gentiles,</hi> and all the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Hereticks of their times. <hi>Baſil</hi> being of the more reſerved temper, we find him not in the <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit</hi> till after he was thirty years of Age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſil</hi> being ordained Prieſt by <hi>Mile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The entry of <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to holy Orders of Prieſthood.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> performs the Prieſtly Office with all Sanctity, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, Eloquence and <hi>Learning:</hi> and knowing that nothing conduceth more to the dignity of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> then a holy life, he excites many Perſons by his own Example to a Singular <hi>Piety.</hi> After ſome ſmall ſpace ſpent in ſo extraordinary converſation, the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> died, the <hi>See</hi> became Vacant, and as in Popular Elections there are generally conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>People</hi> were divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their opinions concerning the Succeſſion of that <hi>See.</hi> Thoſe that lived a more retired and Religious life, and were favourers of ſuch a conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, were zealous for the Election of <hi>Baſil;</hi> the others who where averſe to Hereſies, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more numerous, choſe one <hi>Euſebius,</hi> a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of a great Sanctity, to the Epiſcopal Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The more religious perſons were highly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed, that not only a perſon of ſuch Holineſs and Learning as <hi>Baſil,</hi> was rejected, but that a Lay-man ſhould be preferred before him: which occaſioned a great Contention between <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Baſil.</hi> The Fewd could not poſſibly be appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but a Schiſm muſt have preſently aroſe in the Church, had not the Humility and Prudence of <hi>Baſil</hi> prevented it. Love and Anger both are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:132826:16"/> which abſence removes; He therefore to appeaſe the Indignation of <hi>Euſebius</hi> conceived againſt him, and to cool the Ardors that many of the people had for him, retires into the <hi>Pontick Wilderneſs;</hi> and there by the banks of the River <hi>Iris,</hi> near the <hi>Euxine Sea,</hi> he lived in a Solitary, yet active piety; four years he there ſpent in Prayers, and Studies, and Preaching to the Barbarous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Inhabiters of thoſe Deſarts. So our excellent <hi>Baſil,</hi> like a good <hi>Jonah</hi> would willingly be caſt overboard, to prevent the ſhipwrack of the Church by Schiſm and Sedition. In his Solitude he was bleſſed with the Company of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Divine. In the ſociety of that moſt admirable perſon, he neither wanted a Church nor Academy. And that theſe Glorious perſons might not be diſturbed in actions of Religion, <hi>Baſils</hi> aged Mother the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent <hi>Emmelia</hi> accompanied them in that Solitude, and became the careful Caterer to provide them Herbs for their late Supper. Incredible there was their pains, the wild people thought <hi>Angels</hi> had deſcended to be their Gardians, and Teachers: Multitudes flockt to their Sermons; many were Civilized and Sanctified by them. Whilſt <hi>Baſil</hi> in this retirement enjoyed a perfect tranquility, the Churches abroad were infinitely tormented with the <hi>Arrian</hi> Perſecution. <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperor had embraced that Hereſie which he endeavoured by all Cruelties to propagate every where; the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chriſtians were perſecuted with Baniſhments, Deprivations of their Eſtates, Confiſcation of their Goods, Impriſonments and death it ſelf; whilſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:132826:16"/> the <hi>Arrian Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> took this occaſion boldly to ſpread that wicked opinion, by Sermons and Writings. They came to <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> where they raiſed a great Contention againſt <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and that part of the Church which adhered to him. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> was a better man, then a Divine; fitter to govern the Church, then to diſpute. <hi>Cappadocia</hi> now knew the need of two ſuch Excellent perſons as <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Gregory</hi> were. <hi>Baſil</hi> imagined he could not enjoy that Heavenly Tranquility, which he ſo much deſired, if any diſguſt remained in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> his breaſt: he rightly conceived that the love of God, which he aſpired to, could not burn in brighteſt Ardours, if it had not conſumed all that rancour, his <hi>Biſhop</hi> had conceived againſt him. Whereupon out of his beloved Deſarts he writes to <hi>Euſebius</hi> the moſt Pathetick Letters, that Eloquence heightned with Humility, Affection, Sorrow, and tenderneſs could indite. Thoſe very Letters which work in the Reader ſtrange violence of paſſions, moved not at all <hi>Euſebius:</hi> the old <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi> was peeviſh, whereupon <hi>Baſil</hi> with a profound Reverence and Humility writes a moſt ſubmiſſive and paſſionate Letter to a whole Synod of <hi>Biſhops</hi> met at <hi>Tiana,</hi> that they would intercede to his <hi>Biſhop,</hi> that he would ſend his Pacificatory Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to him into the <hi>Wilderneſs:</hi> but ſtill the old <hi>Biſhop</hi> continued angry; not the intreaties of <hi>Baſil,</hi> nor the Authority of the Synod could move him. But the <hi>Arrians</hi> aſſault him, now his Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be torn, the <hi>City</hi> was peſtered with the flocking of thoſe Hereticks: If the <hi>Metropolis</hi> was ſubdued
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:132826:17"/> ubdued, the inferiour <hi>Sees</hi> would ſuddenly yield. <hi>Euſebius</hi> though of an undaunted Courage, yet was of meaner Learning; who like a Pilot, not fearing the waves, yet wanted dexterity to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage the <hi>Veſſel.</hi> A General, though he is fearleſs of death, has a ſtrong arm, and an active body, and can deal blows enough amongſt his Enemies, yet cannot ſecure his Army, if he want Policy. Stratagems and ordering of the <hi>Battalia</hi> are equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neceſſary to Victory, as Courage and Valour. In this great confuſion of the Churches of <hi>Cappa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docia,</hi> with theſe dreadful conflicts with the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereticks, it was eaſily diſcovered there wanted ſome Excellent perſons, who with equal skill and Valour muſt oppoſe the rage and fury of this perſecution. And now this good old <hi>Biſhop</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, now his paſſion yields to Reaſon. The Church muſt be ſuccoured, <hi>Baſil</hi> is wanting. Whereupon he haſtens a Meſſenger to him, who receives the Meſſage of his <hi>Biſhops</hi> reconciliation with infinite reſentments of joy and kindneſs: and ſo looking upon this Meſſage as from <hi>Heaven,</hi> he haſtens to <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> where he falls proſtrate at the <hi>Biſhops</hi> feet; who having caſt off all his former rancour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, entertains him with all the Expreſſions of love and tenderneſs. As the Earth which has been cruſted over with Froſt, and lain covered with Snow, by the Sun beams ſweetly diſplayed on her, is freed from thoſe cold and uncomely gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and preſently appears in a richer gaiety of Herbs and Flowers: So that Soul of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> poſſeſs'd too long with Furies, Indignation and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:132826:17"/> Anger, being cleanſed by the <hi>Angel</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> is now more gloriouſly inhabited by the Divine paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of love and kindneſs. <hi>Euſebius</hi> his affection and endearments to <hi>Baſil,</hi> infinitely exceeded his anger. <hi>Baſil</hi> cheriſhes theſe new affections with all prudence, with all vigilance, with all tenderneſs and reverence imaginable; ſo managing his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, that his very looks, his geſtures, his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as well as his language, ſhould ſpeak his love, his reſpect and his fidelity to <hi>Euſebius.</hi> All which he ſo diſcreetly and conſtantly performed, that <hi>Euſebius</hi> was wholly turned into love and a great eſteem for <hi>Baſil.</hi> By which means <hi>Euſebius</hi> retains the name of <hi>Biſhop,</hi> but <hi>Baſil</hi> performs the Office; <hi>Baſil</hi> reformed the Clergy, <hi>Baſil</hi> commanded the Laity, <hi>Baſil</hi> withſtood the Hereticks, and yet paid all the due homage of obedience and honour to <hi>Euſebius. Baſil</hi> dared the Hereticks to diſputation; <hi>Baſil</hi> conſtantly preached againſt them; by the quickneſs and ſubtilty of the one, &amp; the Eloquence and Piety of the other, he ſettled the wavering Church, and obtained a moſt glorious victory over the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereticks. The waves muſt now yield a paſſage to that Ship that is ſteered by <hi>Baſilius.</hi> The Army cannot but be victorious, where <hi>Baſil</hi> is the head of it. The old <hi>Biſhop</hi> is drawing to the grave with joy and a great tranquility; he receives the meſſage of death delivered to him by a Feaver. Happy he was to live to thoſe days wherein he ſaw his Church, as houſes, when flames are about them, yet ſecured; as perſons in danger of the Plague, yet freed from the very fear of Infection. <hi>Baſil</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:132826:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> performs to his now dying <hi>Biſhop</hi> all the offices which humanity and piety ſuggeſt: which ſo poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd the good Soul of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that when he was commending it to <hi>Baſil,</hi> he muſt lay his body in the arms of <hi>Baſil:</hi> in the hands of <hi>Baſil</hi> he muſt dye; <hi>Baſil</hi> muſt cloſe his eyes; he would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this World, till he had given teſtimonies of a perfect reconciliation and amity; that they, who were once ſeparated in this life, when the City received one, and the Wilderneſs the other, in the ſucceeding and ever-glorious life might have an eternal union: where they might be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained in the felicity of a perpetual joy, from the fruition of one God, in one everlaſting habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to live for ever and ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> after he had performed <note place="margin">The entrance of <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> into the Holy Orders of Prieſthood.</note> the Office of a Deacon with vaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, he enters into Holy Orders of Prieſthood, which he managed with all piety and induſtry. His Sermons were conſtant; he drew the whole World after him; the piety of them were ſo admirable, and their Eloquence ſo ſtupendious. At <hi>Antioch</hi> he devoted himſelf wholly to ſtudy, and preaching, the affairs of the Church being managed by the Biſhop of that See. So buſineſs forced him not from his ſtudy, but in a great ſerenity he prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelf for exquiſite, yet continual preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. So great a crowd of people daily throng'd to the Church, that the Pulpit was altered from its ancient place, which was in the Chancel, into the body of the Church; where the people, ſtanding
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:132826:18"/> round about him, might readily attend to that torrent of Holineſs and Eloquence. The <hi>Athenian</hi> Orator, that the noiſe and tumult of the people might not diſturb him, whilſt he was pronouncing his brave Orations, conſtantly uſed to repeat them on the Banks of the Haven, that he who was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd at the rouling of the waves, might like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe enjoy an undiſturbed mind amidſt the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours and contentions of the people. But this great man commanded the people to quietneſs, every one fearing leſt any noiſe ſhould hinder them from hearing any ſentence flowing from that golden mouth. The anger that <hi>Euſebius</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived againſt <hi>Baſil,</hi> forced him into the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; but the Schiſm between the two Biſhops of <hi>Antioch,</hi> elected by two different parties, made <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> the ſecond time try the ſweetneſs of the Deſarts. As yet that cuſtom prevailed of the peoples power in electing the Biſhop; a Rite which indeed was uſed in ſeveral Ages of the Church; which no more vindicates the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> Ordination of Miniſters, then the Kings no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Biſhops to the Sees, and Patrons pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting of Clerks to their Benefices, deſtroy the Epiſcopal Ordination. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> thought the Briars and Thorns of the Deſarts were incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably leſs troubleſom, then the Schiſms of the Church. But the <hi>Antiochians</hi> are impatient; <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> muſt return; they can endure no longer the abſence of ſo brave a Preacher. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns privately to <hi>Antioch;</hi> with what joy did this news fill the City? how tedious was that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:132826:19"/> night to them! how long ſeem'd every hour till they ſaw <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in the Pulpit! Early in the morning, did the <hi>Antiochians</hi> haſten to the Church, expecting <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> they knew he could be no longer out of the Pulpit. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> failed not their expectation. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> comes to Church, he haſtens firſt to the Altar, where he pays his devotion to his bleſſed and deareſt Lord. After a Reverence done to the Archbiſhop, he aſcends the Pulpit. What paſſions appeared in the <hi>Antiochians</hi> countenances? at the ſame time, their faces gave the indication of Joy and Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: their eyes were full of tears; the ſacred pavement was ſlippery with that holy water; the Fountains of thoſe Rivers was Love and Joy: ſo Clouds kindly melt into gentle Rain, by the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter influence of the Sun. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> for twelve years, which he ſpent during the time that he was Presbyter at <hi>Antioch,</hi> was aſſiduous in preaching, prayer and ſtudy. His honour and affection that he had for his Archbiſhop, was infinitely entire; he perceiving, that the Sermons of <hi>Flavianus</hi> were not ſo frequented as his own, would repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the peoples temerity; in the midſt of his Sermons would make an Harangue in the praiſe of the Archbiſhop, preferring the Sermons of him, to thoſe of his own; extolling the judiciouſneſs, gravity and ponderous Divinity, and reflecting with ſome diminutions on his own rapidneſs and impetuouſneſs. This glorious action endeared him to the Archbiſhop, with whom he continued a perfect amity, and rendred himſelf more amiable
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:132826:19"/> to the multitude; who plainly perceived that amidſt the Acclamations of the whole City, nay the Applauſe and honour of the whole World, he ſought not his honour from men, but endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to receive it from God. In the third year of his Presbyterſhip, the dreadful commotion hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd, wherein the Citizens in a wild fury threw down the Statues of the Emperor and Empreſs; which caſt <hi>Chryſostom</hi> himſelf into ſuch a vaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of mind, that for ſeven days together he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired to his Chamber, as not being able to look upon that people, who, though they had attended ſo long to his admirable preaching, ſhould throw themſelves headlong into ſuch an inexpreſſible phrenzy. The ſeventh day recollecting his Spirit, he aſcends the Pulpit: never people wanted more an admirable Preacher, and never people fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with a more incomparable man. They ſtood in need of Lenitives and Corroſives, no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ever knew better how to apply them. Their crime was ſo great, that the very ſharpeſt expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, a tongue dipt in Vinegar and Gall, ſufficed not to chaſtiſe their inſolent Treaſons; and yet they were ſo filled with the apprehenſions of their guilt, the horrour of ſo dreadful a Fact did ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie them, that their own conſciences prepared wracks, and wheels for them, and they were dead before the ſentence was pronounced againſt them. The Citizens themſelves became living Ghoſts. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> therefore as a moſt excellent Phyſician, ſeeing a Patient lye ſick of a deſperate wound, which ſtands in need of the moſt ſearching Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſives,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:132826:20"/> and yet of a languiſhing and fainting mind, prepares his Patient by Cordials to receive ſharper Medicines: ſo he raiſes the drooping Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Citizens, and enlivens them by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly comforts, and inſtructions, and afterwards ſcourges them with a moſt eloquent detection of their Villanies, and dreadful denunciation of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Judgments. His Sermons he managed ſo pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and dexterouſly, that they obtained his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired effect. Some time after a ſharp reprehenſion of that rebellious frenzy, he would raiſe ſome comfort in their Spirits by an <hi>Elogium</hi> of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors perſon, and qualities: ſome time promiſing them a happy ſucceſs from the Prudence, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and gravity of <hi>Flavianus,</hi> who undertook to intercede for them; whereby at the ſame time he gained a greater reſpect from his Auditors, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared himſelf to the Archbiſhop, and ingratiated himſelf into the Emperors eſteem: and thus for twelve years he ſo prudently managed the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his Prieſthood, that his fame flew through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World: his name was ſo celebrated in the Emperors Court, that it occaſioned his removal from <hi>Antioch,</hi> to the Archiepiſcopal See of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us behold our Prieſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated Biſhops; now we ſhall behold <note place="margin">The entry of <hi>Baſil</hi> into the Metropoliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal See of <hi>Caeſarea.</hi>
               </note> them with their Croſiers; now advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the higheſt dignities. But with their honour we ſhall behold their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions and troubles. Theſe Mountains of Piety and Learning are now ſtruck with Lightning and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:132826:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> Thunder: The Tranquility of the Wilderneſs is changed into a violent ſtorm; their Retirements and Studies are turned into the troubles and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions of the Court and Church: now they are not more glorious in holineſs and honour, then perſecuted by Envy and Rage. When they entred upon their Epiſcopal dignities, they launched in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Sea of trouble, where they found no reſt, till the grave had prepared a Repoſe for them. Upon the death of <hi>Euſebius, Baſil,</hi> to avoid the Epiſcopal Authority, retired, and fled from <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarea. Valens</hi> the Emperour ſent his Praefect of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> if poſſible, to procure the inſtalling of an <hi>Arrian</hi> Biſhop into that Metropolitical See. The Neighbouring Catholick Biſhops, knowing of what conſequence to the univerſal Church, the Election of <hi>Baſil</hi> would be, all unaminouſly haſten to <hi>Caeſarea.</hi> The aged Father of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Divine, expecting a Bier to carry him to the grave, rather than a Chariot to bring him to <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to undertake that journey: the great Zeal he had to oppoſe the <hi>Arrian</hi> deſigns, and the vaſt love he had for the promoting of the purity of the Churches Doctrine, and eſtabliſhing the Churches peace, revived his drooping Spirits, and ſeemed to reſtore him to a Juvenile vigour. The Election was managed by the <hi>Arrian</hi> party with fury and paſſion. But at length the Conſtancy of the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Chriſtians prevailed; <hi>Baſil</hi> is Elected, after enquiry, is found, by violence forced to <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> where the Provincial Biſhops waited for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being reſolved not to depart, till they had
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:132826:21"/> confirmed the Church againſt the <hi>Arrian</hi> fury by the Conſecration of <hi>Baſil, Anno</hi> 369.</p>
            <p>The Emperour <hi>Arcadius,</hi> the whole <note place="margin">The Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick of <hi>Constantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
               </note> Court and City of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> were ſo ſatisfied with the Virtues, Eloquence, and great Accompliſhments of <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,</hi> that they reſolved no other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but he, ſhould ſit in the Archiepiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal See. But a great queſtion aroſe, how they ſhould procure the Aſſent of that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to accept of that Eccleſiaſtical dignity. And the people of <hi>Antioch,</hi> being ſeditious and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to mutinies; it would be difficult to wreſt <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> (averſe to Eccleſiaſtical honours) out of the hands of that people, who would rather loſe their lives, then the Comfort of their lives, the brave Sermons of <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi> But <hi>Eutropius</hi> the Lord Chamberlain of the Emperors Houſhold, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted <hi>Arcadius</hi> that he would certainly by an innocent contrivance bring <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople.</hi> The Emperour committed the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the Affairs to <hi>Eutropius;</hi> who imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately diſpatched ſome Perſons of Quality to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> with Letters to <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> commanding him in the name of <hi>Arcadius,</hi> upon the account of ſome important affairs, to attend him in a City called by <hi>Zozom.</hi> l. 28. 2. <hi>Pagras,</hi> ſome miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from <hi>Antioch. Chryſostom</hi> not dreaming of <hi>Eutropius</hi>'s deſign, at the place and time waited on him. <hi>Eutropius</hi> at the firſt meeting, roundly told him the Emperors intentions, and deſires. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> refuſed, as being unwilling to leave
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:132826:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> that People, over whom he had ſo abſolute a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and from whom he received ſuch an entire affection. But <hi>Eutropius</hi> was peremptory, he commanded him to be carried into the Chariot; The Charioter muſt obey <hi>Eutropius,</hi> and not lend an ear to the prayers of <hi>Chryſostom;</hi> on he drives, and with hard journeys arrives at <hi>Constantinople:</hi> where the Emperour and the Court receive him with all ſentiments of love and honour, and the people with all joyful Acclamations. Virtue is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways dog'd at the heels by Envy. <hi>Theophilus</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> being then at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> hugely oppoſed <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> Election, and reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly refuſed to be preſent at his Conſecration. That See, the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> Archbiſhop deſigned for a Prieſt of his own Church, who had obliged him by the faithful conduct of this affair: In the War between <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour, and <hi>Eugenius</hi> the Tyrant, he entruſted him with a noble preſent and two Letters, the one to <hi>Eugenius,</hi> the other to <hi>Theodoſius;</hi> with this Commiſſion, that he ſhould deliver neither of the Letters, until the Victory was obtained; and to the Triumpher, who had confirm'd himſelf in the Imperial Dignity, the Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter directed to him with the gifts ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, and the other preſently conſumed in the flames: But as Treaſon ſeldom ſucceeds, baſe and treacherous actions generally are diſcover'd. One of the Servants of this Prieſt ſtole his Letters, and immediately carried them to the Court of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> and deliver'd them into the hands of <hi>Eutro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius,</hi> who reſerved them to make uſe of them as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:132826:22"/> occaſion ſerved. <hi>Eutropius</hi> goes to <hi>Theophilus</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> not deſires, but commands him to conſecrate <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> he peremptorily denies, and with indignation; whereupon <hi>Eutro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius</hi> ſhews him thoſe unworthy and hypocritical Letters; at which <hi>Theophilus</hi> is ſurprized with a trembling aſtoniſhment, and begs pardon, and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of <hi>Eutropius,</hi> and promiſed him to conſecrate <hi>Chryſostom;</hi> which he performed <hi>Anno</hi> 398.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſil</hi> having governed the Church <note place="margin">The manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Epiſcopal Function by <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> under the power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> the management of all affairs being committed to him, by that aged and grave Biſhop; there was no neceſſity of making any altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that Church, which he had governed with ſo much prudence and ſanctity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> on the contrary, ſucceeding <hi>Necta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> in the Archiepiſcopal See of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> found a licentious Clergy, a looſe and a debauch'd City. <hi>Nectarius</hi> from being a Praefect, was advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to that Eccleſiaſtical Throne, and he though he was a perſon of a ſound Faith, and of no mean Abilities, which he bravely exerciſed to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of Hereticks; yet bringing with him the ſplendour and pomp of the Court into his Palace, the Reins of Diſcipline, which in a more auſtere ſanctity bridled the manners of the Clergy and people, he let looſe by Luxury and Pomp: which ingratiated him very much into the favour of the Court; and being a perſon of a ſound Faith, and great reſolution againſt all Hereſies, gave him a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:132826:22"/> brave eſteem in the eyes of the World. He was a great abhorrer of Avarice, and nobly ſpent the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of the Church; but by remitting of the ſeverity of Eccleſiaſtical diſcipline, a way was made for the more licentious converſation of the Clergy; which ſpread it ſelf not only into the Court, but City likewiſe: ſo that there ſeemed an univerſal defection from thoſe rigours which made Chriſtianity ſo glorious in the World. <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> being bred up in ſolitude, and Auſterities, knowing no other Pomp or Luxury but a crouded Church attending upon his divine Eloquence, and being naturally addicted to Auſterities, he was more prone, by the manner of life he uſed, to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh thoſe Excreſcences out of the Church. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, as ſoon as he enter'd upon his Epiſcopal dignity, he betook himſelf to his old courſe of life, conſtantly to preach: and that he might not ſeem in the leaſt to diſſemble his intentions, he with a ſweet torrent of Eloquence ſharply inveighs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the viciouſneſs of Chriſtians, eſpecially of the Clergy, publickly threatning a deprivation of thoſe of the Clergy, who continued in a looſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. This, though it procured the hatred of the Clergy, yet infinitely endeared him to the City: now he is become their darling and favourite, now in every Shop there are the Elogiums of <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom,</hi> every Boy ſings the felicity of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople:</hi> How happy was that See in an Archbiſhop of the greateſt holineſs, induſtry and Eloquence in the World? What he threatned, he punctually performed; many of the Clergy, who neglected
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:132826:23"/> his admonitions, were preſently deprived of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Authority, and removed from the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar. This laid the foundation of a great <hi>odium,</hi> which the Clergy conceived againſt him, and of his after-troubles. He was repreſented cruel, proud and arrogant. An unreaſonable paſſage of <hi>Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phion,</hi> a Deacon of the Church of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> whom he dearly loved, much heightned the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the Clergy: for in the Conſiſtory, as <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> was examining the Prieſts, <hi>Seraphion</hi> cries out, Holy Father, you will never rid the Church of Impiety, till you drive them out with the Rod; a rigorous and an ill-timed paſſage. But ſtill <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostom</hi> is the Peoples darling, and the Clergy that hated his Rigours, admired his Parts and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. But <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> confined not his ſeverity to the Church, but it flew about the City; nay, it ſtaid not there, but it enter'd into the Court. There was no vitious Citizen, let him be of never ſo great Authority and Riches; no vitious Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, let him be of never ſo unlimited Power and Greatneſs, but felt the ſharpneſs of his Eloquence, and was threatned with Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures. This enrages the Court againſt him, ſcorning that the Grandeur of the Eaſtern Empire ſhould be ſubject to the tongue of an <hi>Antiochian</hi> Prieſt, whom they had but lately raiſed to the <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolitan</hi> See. Whilſt his ſeverities were confined within the Church walls, <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſhined with extraordinary luſtre in the eyes of the Court; but when it reach'd the Courtiers Luxury, Pride, Cruelty and Avarice, all their eſteem of him was
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:132826:23"/> turned into hatred and indignation. So all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons love not their own concerns be touch'd; the Clergy did not love that their own Vices, but the Courtiers Enormities ſhould be ſeverely repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended; the Courtiers likewiſe are vaſtly pleaſed with the Reformation of the Church, whilſt they remain enamoured with their own deformities. And this corruption in the manners proceeds from the miſtake of Religion, who ſuppoſe it a remedy for others, but not for their own ſins: or from a ſtrange partiality, whereby they are prone to magnifie the Vices of others, and leſſen their own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſil</hi> was freed from all thoſe inconveniences: The Court had no reſidence in his City; he ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded a devout and ſevere Biſhop, by whoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority he had formerly modelled his Church. He was a perſon of a ſweet and brave temper, and exceedingly prudent, and ſo could free himſelf from thoſe Rocks, on which others perhaps might have ſplit. But that which moſt conduced to the inteſtine tranquility of his See, was the continual perſecutions to which it was obnoxious. Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made the Church of <hi>Cappadocia</hi> ſevere and holy: Perſecution performed that, which <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> deſired to obtain by Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> came to govern that Church which was debauch'd by the remiſneſs of a former Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, and degenerated into Pride and Luxury, which a great Peace, a vaſt Trade and Commerce, affluence of Wealth, the glory and pomp of the Court had occaſioned. The playing of the golden
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:132826:24"/> beams of the Sun, makes us throw off our Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, when the bluſtering North wind cauſe us ſtraiter to bind them to us. It is eaſie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to Reaſon an afflicted mind, but difficult to reduce to ſobriety a proſperous Criminal.</p>
            <p>The Eaſtern Church at that time was <note place="margin">The conteſts and conflicts of <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> with the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks.</note> vexed with the <hi>Eunomians, Sabellians,</hi> but more chiefly by the <hi>Arrians. Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens</hi> himſelf, a perſon of very great Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, but of greater Impiety, violently perſecuted the faithful Chriſtians. He had baniſhed moſt of the Biſhops from their Sees, and inſtead of pious and holy Prelates, the Church was peſter'd and almoſt ruin'd by wicked and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing Biſhops. <hi>Valens,</hi> when he had carried Trophies of his own wickedneſs through moſt of the parts of the Eaſtern Empire, was dreadfully enraged, that <hi>Cappadocia</hi> ſhould ſtand ſo firm againſt all the furies and aſſaults of Hell; he in his own perſon leads his Army down into <hi>Cappa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>docia,</hi> attended with a numerous Train of the moſt learned of his <hi>Arrian</hi> Chaplains, not queſtioning but that he ſhould either terrifie <hi>Baſil</hi> into obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or elſe rid <hi>Cappadocia</hi> of that great Prelate. But what courſe ſhould he uſe? what? ſhould he order an Army of his Heretical Prieſts and Biſhops againſt one <hi>Baſil?</hi> No: he had gained ſo many notorious and famous Victories over the learnedſt Opponents in the World, that none of them durſt undertake him. And it may move a pretty laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to obſerve, that when the greateſt Scholars of the <hi>Arrian</hi> Faction trembled at the very
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:132826:24"/> thoughts of a conteſt with <hi>Baſil,</hi> the Emperours Cook <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> challenged <hi>Baſil</hi> to diſpute; whom when <hi>Baſil</hi> had moſt egregiouſly baffled, not without angry ſmile thus ſays to the people: Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literate <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> would diſpute, the propereſt place for a Cook is the Kitchin; Can his tongue, which is only fit for the taſting of Sauces, and his head filled with the fume of Meat, comprehend or diſcourſe of Spiritual things? <hi>Valens</hi> aſſaulted <hi>Baſil</hi> by a Praefect of his Army, who firſt allured him by the promiſes of the greateſt Preferments; and told him the glory of being honoured by the Emperor, and the great Officers of his Army was not to be refuſed by him. To which <hi>Baſil</hi> gallant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly replied, Chriſtianity is not made illuſtrious by the dignity of Perſons, but by the integrity of Faith At which, the Praefect grew enraged, and thunder'd out the heavieſt menaces, and thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſted him; Fear'ſt thou not the confiſcation of thy Eſtate? to which <hi>Baſil</hi> preſently reply'd, No; all the Riches I enjoy are theſe poor Rags I have on my back, and a few Books. Not Baniſhment? No; I am a Stranger in the World; the Earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof. Not Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? No; this worn body of mine will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure above one ſtroke. Not death? No; I am almoſt already dead, and you will ſooner ſend me to the Grave. After he had thus anſwered the Praefect, he ends that diſcourſe with a paſſage full of ſweetneſs and courage; Sir, I ſpeak nothing in contempt of your Dignity, it is not for us faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Chriſtians to ſpeak roughly to the meaneſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:132826:25"/> perſon, much leſs one of ſo great a quality as your ſelf; but we are obliged to profeſs in the Cauſe of our God, all torments are a delight to us. This carriage of <hi>Baſil</hi> filled the Praefect with the Reverence of him. The Praefect haſtens to the Emperour, giving this only account of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, <hi>Baſil</hi> hath conquered us. This not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, <hi>Valens</hi> ſends for <hi>Baſil,</hi> whom he attacks by all the arts imaginable. Thouſands of profits he propoſed, as many tortures and utmoſt extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties threatned; But nothing moved <hi>Baſil,</hi> whoſe hopes were Heaven, and fears Hell. Yet <hi>Valens</hi> perſiſted in his determination of baniſhing him, which he altered on ſeveral accounts. <hi>Valens</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring the piety of <hi>Baſil,</hi> managed with ſo great a Prudence, went to the Church to obſerve the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor and carriage of Catholick Chriſtians in the performance of Divine Offices; where coming and ſeeing <hi>Baſil</hi> ſitting in his Chair, and the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Chriſtians ſtanding round about him, all in a poſture noting the higheſt reverence of the Divine Majeſty, and hearing them ſing their Hymns and Hallelujahs with the greateſt fervour, joy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, and taking cognizance of the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all the Divine Service and Worſhip, he was ſtruck with ſuch a horrour, that he fell into an univerſal trembling; that as he approached to offer his gift at the Altar, had he not been ſupported by one of the Prieſts that aſſiſted <hi>Baſil,</hi> in a great amaze and aſtoniſhment he had fallen to the ground. So great an influence hath Religion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly performed, upon her very Enemies. Divine
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:132826:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> actions done with fervour and devotion, carry Majeſty as well as ſweetneſs with them. The very apprehenſion of the fact ſtruck <hi>Valens</hi> with ſuch an horrour, that three times the Pen, as he was to ſign the Decree of Baniſhment, fell out of his hands; a great trembling ſeized on him. His only Son <hi>Galates</hi> fell ſick; <hi>Valens</hi> had ſo great an appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of <hi>Baſils</hi> ſanctity, that he ſent for him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving his prayers ſhould recover his Son; <hi>Baſil</hi> came and offered up his prayers for the health of the young Prince, in whom there preſently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſigns of recovery; on which <hi>Baſil</hi> goes to the Emperour, and tells him, Sir, hinder not the efficacy of our prayers by the ſupplications of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, let none of that wicked Faith approach your Son, and he will recover. At which the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour was angry; which <hi>Baſil</hi> perceiving, he took his leave with theſe words, The will of the Lord be done. The Emperours Chaplains offered their Devotions for the young Prince, but they wanted <hi>Baſils</hi> Faith; he relapſes, and dies. Theſe ſingular remarks of God's Providence, with the admirable prudence and ſweetneſs of <hi>Baſil,</hi> made ſuch an impreſſion on the Emperour and Empreſs, that when all the Catholick Biſhops of the Eaſtern Empire were baniſhed, <hi>Baſil</hi> continued till his death in his See. But how great was the calamity and vaſt unhappineſs, that the Great <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſhould be twice baniſhed, and that, through the Enmity which Catholick Biſhops had againſt him, and the great indignation of a Catholick Emperor and Empreſs, his auſtere courſe of life rendred
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:132826:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> him unpleaſing to the Court. The former Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>Nectarius</hi> was frequent at Entertainments, and did not ſeldom feaſt the <hi>Constantinopolitan</hi> Nobility; <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſo totally retired, that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver entertained any at a Banquet, nor ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived an invitation, which rendred him unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the Court. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> was of that Spirit, as in defence of the meaneſt, he would oppoſe the greateſt Perſon in the World. <hi>Eudoxia</hi> the Empreſs was deſirous to enjoy the eſtate of a Widow, whoſe Husband was unjuſtly put to death; to preſerve her Lands, and maintain her Fatherleſs Children, ſhe addreſs'd her ſelf to <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> who was ever ready to hear the complaints, and relieve the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of miſerable perſons; he goes to <hi>Eudoxia,</hi> and there in the behalf of this Widow, uſes ſome Language which the Empreſs could not bear, and raiſed an implacable hatred againſt him. <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> his irreconcileable enemy, knowing the diſpoſition of <hi>Eudoxia,</hi> that as ſhe was reſolved, ſo ſhe would ruine any man ſhe hated, waited all opportunities to work his deſigned miſchief againſt <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> to heighten the rage of <hi>Eudoxia.</hi> There were three Eloquent Biſhops of that age who came to <hi>Conſtantinople, Severianus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Gabale, Antiochus</hi> a <hi>Syrian</hi> Biſhop, and <hi>Acacius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Beraea,</hi> all Emulators of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> who uſed their utmoſt endeavours to alienate the minds of the Citizens from their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Archbiſhop, which they almoſt effected. For <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> to reduce to order the <hi>Aſiatick</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſubject to his Archiepiſcopal See, took a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:132826:26"/> journey to <hi>Epheſus,</hi> in which he mightily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured the Reformation of the Clergy, and the ſettling of the Church. He depoſed fourteen <hi>Novatian</hi> Biſhops, threw ſeveral of their vicious Clergy out of their places, which made him to be eſteemed cruel and inſolent. And thus his Rivals in Eloquence and Preaching, did not abſtain from ſecret yet intelligible traducing of him. <hi>Eudoxia</hi> favoured them in theſe actions; But <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> returns; <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> aſcends the Pulpit; and in one Sermon totally reconciles the City to him. Thoſe Stars of Oratory could give no light, whilſt the Sun of Eloquence ſhined ſo clearly in the tongue of <hi>Chryſostom;</hi> who being informed of the endeavours of thoſe Biſhops, and the attempts of <hi>Eudoxia,</hi> them he threatned with ſuſpenſion, and to give a publick <hi>Manifeſto,</hi> he took cognizance of the deſign of the Empreſs; he took greater li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in one Excellent Sermon to declaim againſt the Vices and Impertinences of Feminine Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. She knowing what <hi>Chryſostom</hi> aimed at, and it was her repute, that <hi>Chryſostoms</hi> Eloquence blackned, her anger burned up to a more exceſſive rage, which ſhe politickly concealed, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to make a perfect reconciliation between <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> and <hi>Severianus;</hi> which when ſhe could not accompliſh by any preſwaſions, ſhe took her young Son the Prince <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> being but eight years of age, and laid him at <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> feet; an action which carries as forceable Eloquence, as any words that ever flowed from the mouth of <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> which throughly perſwaded <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:132826:27"/> who was entirely and perfectly reconciled to <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verianus,</hi> though he did yet retain a ſecret grudge againſt <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theophilus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> a great enemy of the <hi>Origeniſts,</hi> ſeveral of whom were depoſed by him, many excommunicated, judging <hi>Chryſostom</hi> a favourer of <hi>Origen,</hi> thought there was a fair occaſion offered to accompliſh his deſign againſt him: he goes accompanied with ſeveral Biſhops to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and ſends to <hi>Epiphanius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salamine</hi> in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> there with the <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> Biſhops to meet him, to condemn the works of <hi>Origen.</hi> Some of the <hi>Aegyptian Origenists</hi> fly to <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> who received them with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of ſtrangers; for they were men of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent lives and great learning. <hi>Theophilus,</hi> not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the cuſtom of Biſhops, (who when they arrived to any place, firſt went to the houſe of Prayers) immediately went to the Empreſſes Palace, where Lodgings were provided for him. No ſooner was <hi>Epiphanius</hi> arrived at <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> but <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſends ſome of his Church to him, to invite him to accept of Lodgings at his Palace; but <hi>Epiphanius</hi> refuſed, and ſends to <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſostom</hi> this ſharp meſſage, That he would not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with him that had received <hi>Origeniſts,</hi> and had not condemned the Books of <hi>Origen:</hi> To which <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> by another Meſſenger gave this modeſt and ſober reply, That he had received none into Communion but thoſe who were of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent lives, and as he thought of a ſound Faith; and that it ſeemed very ſevere to condemn the works
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:132826:27"/> of ſo glorious a man, as <hi>Origen</hi> was, without a very ſerious conſideration; and therefore he ſtill deſired <hi>Epiphanius</hi> to take Lodgings in his Palace, for it would be an infinite grief to him to ſee any diſſention between themſelves, and ſo excellent a perſon as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> was: But <hi>Epiphanius</hi> was not to be moved. So we ſee, as in the Moon there are ſpots, the moſt curious of Jewels may have a flaw, and little imperfections in the beſt of men. They afterwards both meet, and are both paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: So that flame that burned in their breaſts towards God, yielded to the worſer fire of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But the Divine Grace who permits the lapſes of good men, preſerves them from great viciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, kept <hi>Epiphanius</hi> from giving conſent to the depoſing of <hi>Chryſoſtom. Theophilus</hi> the Archbiſhop, a man of very great fame for Piety and Vertue, and <hi>Eudoxia</hi> the Empreſs, a perſon that had rare qualities, ſo repreſented <hi>Chryſostom</hi> to <hi>Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> that it is no wonder his paſſions were ſo by aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, when his Judgment was ſo impoſed upon. <hi>Theophilus</hi> gathers a great company of Biſhops to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and there all thoſe Biſhops which the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> or the Arts of his Adverſaries, or all the powers of the Court could make, met at a place called the Oak in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and ſummoned <hi>Chryſostom</hi> to appear before them. He refuſed, and with the higheſt reaſon; for what Authority had the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> Biſhop over the Biſhop of <hi>Constantinople?</hi> or with what Authority or reaſon could they celebrate a Council in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi> without the conſent of <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> Arch-
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:132826:28"/> Archbiſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople? Chryſoſtom</hi> ſent two of his Presbyters to that unlawful Convention of Biſhops, and acquainted them, that their actions were deſtructive of the Churches peace, contrary to the Eccleſiaſtical Canons; and that he refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not to anſwer any crimes laid againſt him, but he rejected an uſurped power, and therefore ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to a General Council. They ſtill perſiſt in their determinations upon his non-appearing. At the fourth ſummons they pronounced a ſentence of his depoſition, which being divulged in the City, filled them with rage and indignation. The whole City is in an uproar; here the very Children and Women cryed, men raged, all haſtened to the Cathedral and Palace of <hi>Chryſostom;</hi> whom they detained all night, which was paſs'd in Prayer and Preaching. They could hardly be filled with a greater ſorrow and amazement, if an Enemy had been ſacking their Town, then they were at the apprehenſions of the loſs of <hi>Chryſoſtom:</hi> but <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> uſes all his Eloquence to perſwade the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to peace, and to behave themſelves with all Reverence and obedience to their Religious Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. O brave mind! provoked to excellent actions by injuries and oppreſſions! So <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> retires to his Palace, where for ſome ſpace he keeps himſelf reſerved, and would not come to the Church: and now <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> ſeems to be in a perpetual night, no joy in that City where their brave Preacher was wanting. <hi>Theophilus</hi> ſeeing the affections of the People for <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> and the rage againſt him, fears an attempt upon his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:132826:28"/> Perſon; the like poſſeſt the reſt of the Biſhops, who wiſely to prevent any danger leave the City and haſten to their reſpective Sees. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives a meſſage from the Emperour, to retire into Exile, that the Souldiers were ready to convey him into the place deſigned for his baniſhment; who fearing his publick departure might occaſion an uproar, and endanger the Perſon of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and Empreſs, privately delivered himſelf into the hands of the Souldiers, and ſo unknown to the City was carried into Exile. But as ſoon as ever the fame of his Baniſhment was ſpread, the people were ſtruck with rage and fury; the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and children run with the greateſt paſſion to the Emperors gate, and there they begg'd and cry'd for <hi>Chryſoſtom:</hi> the men aſſembled in nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous companies, nothing in this City but confuſion, here a company would cry, what Judgments waited upon that City, which was unworthy of <hi>Chryſoſtom!</hi> others, violently railing at the unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful proceedings of the Biſhops that depoſed him. So pitiful were the complaints, ſo dangerous was the inſurrection, that <hi>Arcadius</hi> had no other means left him to quiet that tumultuous City, but with a promiſe of a ſpeedy reſtauration of him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he immediately diſpatched <hi>Burſo</hi> an Eunuch of the Empreſs, with ſpecial commands, to bring <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> back to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> He finding him at <hi>Prenetum</hi> over againſt <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> brings him back to the City, where he was received with all imaginable expreſſions of joy. No City reduced to the greateſt extremity by a potent Enemy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieging
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:132826:29"/> it, could be more filled with the higheſt joy at a ſeaſonable ſuccour and relief, then the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinopolitans</hi> were, at the return of <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi> Their Acclamations were ſo loud, their expreſſions of content ſo various and great, that <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>'s ſatisfaction for his return was leſſened by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate honour they did unto him. But he ſtaid in the Suburbs, and would not enter into the City, nor go into the Pulpit, till he was legally abſolved; till his cauſe was legally heard, and he himſelf found innocent. But this gave no ſatisfaction to the people; they muſt ſee <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in the Church, they muſt hear him preach. Whereupon they ſo preſſed upon <hi>Arcadius,</hi> that he forced <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pulpit, and there to pray and preach, which he performed. In his Benediction they thought themſelves all bleſſed, his Prayers they concluded would pierce the Heavens, and his pious Eloquence convey them to glory. And this courſe for ſome months, to the infinite content of the Citizens, he continued. But over againſt the Church called <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia,</hi> one of the miracles of the World, the place where he uſually preached, the Statue of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs made of Silver, with a rich Mantle over her head, was erected, before which Plays and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes were celebrated. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> looking upon this as a diſhonour done to Almighty God, dehorts the people from ſuch courſes, in a great vehemency maintains the dignity of the Divine Service, with a torrent of the richeſt Oratory againſt Plays and Interludes; that it was an inexpreſſible indignity to Almighty God, that the Acclamations and noiſe of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:132826:29"/> Plays and Interludes, ſhould be heard in the Church where <hi>Halelujahs</hi> are ſung to God; and ſo a diſturbance be given to the Prieſt and holy people that wait about the Altar. Which Sermon coming to the Empreſſes ears, the fire of her rage, which lay ſmothered under the aſhes of diſſimulation, broke out into an open flame againſt him, ſo that ſhe openly threatned his ſecond depoſition; which he receiving in great paſſion, enters the Church, and there makes that ſo famous Sermon which thus begins: <hi>Herodias</hi> ſtill dances, <hi>Herodias</hi> ſtill rages, <hi>Herodias</hi> is ſtill filled with indignation, <hi>Herodias</hi> yet ſeeks for the head of <hi>John</hi> in a Platter. At which the Empreſs was ſo incenſed, that ſhe would hear of no entreaty for a reconciliation with <hi>Chryſoſtom:</hi> But immediately ſends for <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> the old and ſworn enemy of <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> to ſummon a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> there to hear the crimes laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> who juſtly refuſed to appear, affirming that he kept himſelf within his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, with the company of fifty Biſhops of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Piety and Learning, who ſpent their time in prayers and tears. No crimes in that Council were objected againſt <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> only he was charged, that contrary to the Eccleſiaſtical Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, he had preached, not being abſolved, and reſtored to his Church. For in a Council at <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch</hi> it was decreed, that if any Biſhop was depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, he ſhould not be reſtored to any Eccleſiaſtical Dignity, except the number of Biſhops that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored him, exceeded the number that depoſed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:132826:30"/> him. To which <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> made this reply; that his depoſition was unjuſt, unlawful, and in it ſelf null: and that for fear of thoſe inconveniences which might follow a popular tumult, he volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily retired into Exile; that he had not returned, but by the Emperours command; and for fear of the leaſt tranſgreſſion of the Eccleſiaſtical Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, upon his return he ſtaid in the Suburbs, and would not enter into the City, much leſs into the Church, till he was compelled by the Emperors commands, and by the clamours of the people; and withall being perſwaded by the ſuffrage of fifty Biſhops, that were then with him, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his Eccleſiaſtical Function, and that that Canon which was alledged againſt him, was made by an <hi>Arrian</hi> Council in the Cauſe of <hi>Athanaſius:</hi> and here it ſeem'd, a very hard meaſure was offered to <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> that by that Emperor who commanded his return, and forced his preaching, a Council ſhould ſummon and condemn by an <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Canon. The Council was reſolved to ſatisfie their own indignation, and the Empreſſes rage; <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> muſt be baniſhed; <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> muſt be depoſed; the ſentence is again pronounced againſt him; the Emperor brings his Army into the City: But <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> that the people, nor Court, nor Army might be in danger, delivers himſelf again privately into the hands of the Souldiers, who carry him into Baniſhment.</p>
            <p>Their noble extraction entituled <note place="margin">The great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi>
               </note> them to great Revenues: <hi>Baſil</hi> was the Eldeſt Son, <hi>Chryſostom</hi> the only
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:132826:30"/> Son of his Parents: and being both raiſed to great Dignities, they had opportunities of treaſuring up a large Eſtate, but their great Souls could not be confined by Riches. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> at <hi>Antioch</hi> diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted his Eſtate amongſt the poor; <hi>Baſil</hi> retained a great part of his Eſtate till after he was Biſhop. When there fell a great Famine in <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> which threatned the conſuming of moſt of the Citizens; this occaſion this wiſe perſon took to ſhew his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality: for he ſold all his remaining Revenue, to which he laid the Revenues of his Metropoliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal See: by this example, and moſt powerful preaching, he wrought ſo upon the Nobility and Gentry of <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> and the rich Citizens, that they brought to him vaſt ſums of money, which he ſo diſpoſed on, that he brought a plenty into <hi>Caeſarea;</hi> he ſo husbanded his Bank, that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets of the City were conſtantly furniſhed with proviſion. <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> when he was baniſhed, and in perpetual fears through the rude and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Nations, yet received ſuch a ſupply from his Friends at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and other places, that for the Fatherleſs, Widows, Captives, and other diſtreſſed people he had a continual ſupply. Many Captives he redeemed, multitudes of other perſons he furniſhed with neceſſaries, that in his greateſt extremity he thought it his higheſt duty to convert the liberality of others to him, into charity for the furniſhing of others with neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. They both of them in their reſpective Sees, built Hoſpitals, received Strangers, and indeed performed all acts of charity to all ſorts of perſons.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:132826:31"/> So much they partaked of the Divine nature, that they ſeemed wholly to be made up of goodneſs and bounty; by which means the very <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> had them in very great Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſil</hi> took the higheſt care for the <note place="margin">Their great Labours for the peace of the Church.</note> preſervation of the Churches peace, againſt the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereticks: his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours were indefatigable; and having with the aſſiſtance of his beloved friend <hi>Gregory,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> (notwithſtanding the power and fury of the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereticks) quietly ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled the Churches in <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> (O <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> made odious by thoſe proverbs, which rendred the Inhabitants the moſt wicked people in the World, now became glorious by the great profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſtianity, which was made illuſtrious by three Biſhops, the beſt Scholars and holieſt perſons in the Univerſe:) thus the glory of Chriſtianity turns the Briars of the Wilderneſs, into the Roſes of <hi>Sharon.</hi> He then betook himſelf to the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Churches of the whole World, he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled into <hi>Armenia,</hi> and into the adjacent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries of <hi>Cappadocia;</hi> the Weſtern Churches enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a great tranquility under a Catholick Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. To the Biſhops of <hi>Italy, France,</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> he wrote Letters, repreſenting the calamities of the Eaſtern Churches, imploring their Aid. The brave Biſhop of <hi>Millain,</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> gave him his greateſt aſſiſtance; and with the Divine good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and eternal Providence, (notwithſtanding all the perſecutions of <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperor, and all the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:132826:31"/> oppoſitions of the <hi>Arrian</hi> Learning, and Arms could make againſt him) <hi>Cappadocia</hi> was preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as a Virgin not ſpotted with the errours of thoſe times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſostom</hi> ſo earneſtly endeavoured the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Eaſt, that the remoteſt parts of them were happy by the influence of his piety and learning. He undertook, for the expelling of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, a journey of ſome months into <hi>Aſia;</hi> he ſent ſome of his Presbyters to convert the <hi>Goths,</hi> in which they had a noble ſucceſs. He reformed the Churches of <hi>Armenia</hi> and <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained an union with the Weſtern Biſhops, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving an Edict from the Emperor, to deſtroy the Idolatrous Temples in <hi>Phaenicia,</hi> with a command to the Lords of the Emperors Treaſury for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering of money to defray the expences for that imployment, he accepted of the command, and refuſed the money: Out of his own Purſe, and with the charge of other Noble Perſons, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Emperors Edict without the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors expences. So theſe great perſons like the Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Luminaries, emit an happy influence to thoſe Churches, which are far diſtant from them.</p>
            <p>The great inclination that <hi>Baſil</hi> had <note place="margin">The Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and ſlanders caſt on them.</note> to Diſputations, and the vaſt love he had to Learned men, was the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of caſting many ſlanders on him. In his Sermons againſt the <hi>Arrians,</hi> his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies that came to hear him, more to carp, then to learn, would ſnatch away ſome paſſage, that might ſeem to ſavour of the <hi>Sabellian</hi> impiety:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:132826:32"/> Preaching at other times againſt the <hi>Sabellia</hi> Hereſie, ſome ſentence would drop from him, which his Adverſaries would wreſt to <hi>Tritheiſm.</hi> In the Euchariſtical Benediction, with which he concluded his Sermons, having alter'd the Prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by,</hi> though that mutation was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of in many Churches of the Eaſt, and uſed by the moſt Catholick Biſhops of the World, yet his impudent enemies carried away the clamours and impetuous noiſe of <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> and <hi>Eunomia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm;</hi> which defamations, being ſpread abroad, alienated the affections of many of the Eaſtern and Weſtern Biſhops from him. Thoſe wicked revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers by their moſt deſperate ſlanders, had ſo chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the affections of the Citizens of <hi>Neo-Caeſarea,</hi> to whom he was very much endeared by his firſt education, that all the Proteſtations of <hi>Baſil</hi> to the contrary, all the Pathetical Letters he wrote to them, could hardly reduce them to better thoughts of him. How ſtrange is it, that a perſon, who in all his Writings, in all his Sermons, in all his Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nay, who vindicated himſelf bravely from the aſperſions of any indiſcreet language, which might ſeem to juſtifie the calumny of his enemies, yet ſhould be believed to be a great friend to thoſe Hereſies, which he made the whole deſign of his life to overthrow? Yet here was <hi>Baſils</hi> felicity, that his beloved <hi>Gregory</hi> was his defence perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, and the Churches of <hi>Cappadocia</hi> conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertained the honour for him, and the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies could not prevail whilſt <hi>Baſil</hi> lived. <hi>Euſtathius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sebaſtia,</hi> was an extraordinary man,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:132826:32"/> and of a ſtrict and ſevere life; <hi>Baſil</hi> affected him for theſe excellent qualities, and likewiſe being aſſured of the ſoundneſs of his Faith concerning the Trinity, and not knowing of thoſe ſtranger Hereſies which he was broacher of, he received him into the Sacred Communion. <hi>Apollinarius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> a man of very great parts, a great enemy to the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie, a great defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Chriſtian Faith under <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate; who, when that Emperor prohibited Orators to teach the Sons of Chriſtians, turned for the uſe of Chriſtian Children the whole Bible into <hi>Greek</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick verſe, gaining a great Fame in the World, cauſed <hi>Baſils</hi> deſire to be acquainted with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween whom there happen'd a great familiarity; <hi>Baſil,</hi> as yet, being ignorant of ſome deſperate Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, which this learned Biſhop had broached.</p>
            <p>Theſe actions being known in the World, raiſed ſuch an hatred againſt our great Prelate, that moſt of the Eaſtern and Weſtern Biſhops denied a Communion with him. What grief muſt poſſeſs this excellent perſon! now with <hi>Elijah</hi> he would lie fainting, and wiſh to die. What comfort could he have now in the Church of God? that he, who ſo infinitely endeavoured the peace, the unity, the purity of the lives and Faith of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſhould now be denied the communion of the greateſt, and beſt part of <hi>Christendom.</hi> His ſorrow could not be better expreſſed, then by his own Pen; his Letters written to the Eaſtern and Weſtern Biſhops, which do now remain, are glorious Monuments of the greatneſs of his Parts, and the ſweetneſs of his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:132826:33"/> diſpoſition. Not one word dropt from his Pen which ſavoured of anger, but only ſorrow. He did not inflame his Papers with indignation, but watered them with tears; and though as ſoon as ever the Hereſies of <hi>Apollinarius</hi> and <hi>Euſtathius</hi> were detected to him, he Excommunicated them, and deſired of the Eaſtern and Weſtern Biſhops to do the ſame; yet they could hardly procure an opinion of the integrity of his Faith. <hi>Euſtathius</hi> to whom he had ſhewed a kindneſs, wrote a Letter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vective againſt him; yet for fear he ſhould anſwer thoſe vile Satyrs, he abſtained three years together from writing. O that perfection of Chriſtian Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and height of Patience! in theſe actions the meekneſs, the candor, the ſweetneſs of <hi>Baſils</hi> Soul were elucent: he would not lay any impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation upon thoſe, who had unjuſtly received ſo ill an opinion of him, or had aſperſed him with calumnies, and denied a Communion with him; though they were men infinitely inferiour to him in parts, piety, and induſtry. Which procured him after his death an immortal fame; of whom the Schools have given this <hi>Elogium,</hi> That of all the Greek and Latine Fathers, <hi>Baſil</hi> expreſſed himſelf the moſt warily, and with the greateſt caution, in the deepeſt Myſteries of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> contracted not an envy from his Adverſaries by oppoſition of Hereticks, but by his ſevere reprehenſion of Vices. He was taxed with no Hereſie, only they charged him with the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of ſome Religious <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Monks; who, for the Doctrine of <hi>Origen,</hi> were baniſhed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:132826:33"/> by <hi>Theophilus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria:</hi> when indeed he received them not into the Sacred and Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical communion, but into the Foreign, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Strangers. But ſo great was the malice of his Adverſaries againſt him, that they taxed him with Pride, Inſolence, and Arrogance. <hi>Baſil</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſcaped not the imputation of Pride; when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there were great vertues in them, their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude and retirement was eſteemed Pride, when indeed it was Religion; they ſhun'd the unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſociety of men, that they might enjoy the converſation with God and Angels. That which in <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> was called Cruelty and Arrogance, was an implacable hatred againſt Impiety. He was inexorable to all wicked perſons, and could not endure that polluted hands ſhould ſerve at the Altar.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> Praefect of <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Their Courage in the defence of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</note> had in his mind already diſpoſed of a young, beautiful and rich Lady, (the late deceaſe of whoſe Husband had rendred her a ſorrowful Widow) in marriage to one of his kindred. The deſign being diſcovered to that Noble Perſon, ſhe totally refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and manifeſted the abhorrence of a ſecond bed. <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſtill perſiſted in his intentions, which ſhe conſtantly denied. The deſire of her Eſtate ſo enraged him, that he betook himſelf to threats, menacing her with a Confiſcation of her Eſtate, and impriſonment of her perſon. This Lady redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to theſe ſtraits, there was left no other <hi>Aſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum</hi> for her, but what the Church afforded; She
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:132826:34"/> flies to the Altar; <hi>Baſil</hi> receives her into protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which caſt the Praefect into an infinite rage, diſdaining that a Biſhop ſhould deliver ſo rich a Prey out of his hands. The Praefect comes with his ordinary Guard of Souldiers to <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> and goes to the Court of Judicature, where he aſcends the Tribunal, attended and guarded by his Officers and Souldiers, and then ſends orders for <hi>Baſil</hi> to appear before him, which he readily obeyed: and no other crime being laid againſt him, then the Protection of this Lady, was commanded pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to deliver her into the hands of the Praefect, which he reſolutely denied; at which the incenſed Praefect commands him to put off his cloaths, and his Serjeants to prepare their Scourges and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; to which <hi>Baſil</hi> with a Chriſtian ſmile reply'd, that Rivers of blood could not flow from a body ſo conſumed; and it was a great joy to him, that he ſhould change thoſe rags for the Robes of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. But by this time, the news of the Biſhops danger, and of the Praefects barbarous uſing him, alarm'd the Citizens; ſo that Men, Women and Children preſently flew into Arms, and ran with violence to the Court, threatning the Praefect and his Guard with a certain death. <hi>Euſebius,</hi> who little dream'd of ſuch a numerous enemy, at the expectation of death, fell into a great trembling and aſtoniſhment; which <hi>Baſil</hi> perceiving, turned to him, and bad him be of good comfort; for the Citizens Swords ſhould not paſs through the Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, but by his own breaſt, for Chriſtian Biſhops will not be the Authors of the death of their
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:132826:34"/> perſecutors. Whereupon <hi>Baſil</hi> turns to his Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and began to make a Pious and Eloquent Sermon to them. But they ſeeing their Biſhop ſafe, were filled with extraordinary joy, and at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand promiſed all ſecurity to the Praefect; whom he ſafely led through the midſt of his armed Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens. The Lady having this ſecurity, ſpent the reſt of her life with <hi>Macrina,</hi> St. <hi>Baſils</hi> Siſter, in the glorious performances of Charity and Piety. So we ſee Infidelity cruel, but Chriſtianity charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and beneficent; and thoſe, who in proſperity ſwelled with pride and rage, in adverſity become ſneaking and dejected. <hi>Eutropius</hi> the Eunuch, who brought <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Lord High Chamberlain, a Pagan, had ſo extraordinarily inſinuated himſelf into <hi>Arcadius's</hi> favour, that he became the greateſt perſon in the Empire: The affairs of the Commonwealth were more managed by the command of <hi>Eutropius,</hi> then the will of <hi>Arcadius;</hi> all Offices in the Court and Army were at his diſpoſal. One <hi>Theognoſtus,</hi> of Conſular dignity, falls into the diſpleaſure of <hi>Eutropius,</hi> by whoſe procurement he was baniſhed into <hi>Armenia,</hi> and there baſely murdered: his Eſtate was confiſcated, his diſconſolate Widow had been reduced to the greateſt extremities, had ſhe not been ſecured by the ſanctity of the Altar, and the power of <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> who reſiſted the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuous pride, arrogance and cruelty of <hi>Eutro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius:</hi> who to avenge himſelf on the Biſhop, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Law to be enacted for the removing of the Church immunities, and annulling that ſecurity,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:132826:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> which miſerable perſons had at the Altar. In this deceitful felicity he continues, and was advanced to the Conſular dignity. But oh the unconſtancy of humane affairs! when he began to dream of the Imperial Purple, and thought himſelf ſecure in the enjoying of the greateſt honour, that the Eaſt could afford, he falls into the Emperours diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and by that, into the greateſt miſery. His death was decreed: to prevent the Execution of it, and preſerve his miſerable life, he haſtens to the Church, and throws himſelf at the foot of the Altar. Thus the World ſuffers perpetual viciſſitudes, and the higheſt Grandeurs may be leſſened in the eſteem of ſober, and wiſe perſons. This ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that thought himſelf ſo ſafe that the Heavens could not ruine him, and was ſwell'd with ſo high a pride, that he would not ſuffer the very Altar to be a ſhelter for any againſt his fury, is forced to confeſs the impiety of his fact by flying to the Altar; from which, the liberty of protection by a ſevere Law he had taken away. The people, the Souldiers, all haſten to the Church to tear in pieces this wretched man. There is nothing more impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent then Popular paſſions. This <hi>Eutropius</hi> whom the other day they feared, and adored as a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtrial Deity, now they proſecute as the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of men. Whether the people are generally delighted in cruelty, and through a ſtrange im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of mind take pleaſure in the miſeries of others, or elſe it gives them a ſatisfaction in their meaner conditions, to ſee the ruines and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that fall upon the greateſt perſons, is the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:132826:35"/> reaſon, that the Vulgar pour all their indignities and cruelties upon thoſe, who have lapſed from the higheſt honours, I am not to determine; only this is moſt certain, that the Peoples darling, and the Court favourite, if once they fall from that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour they have attained, are proſecuted by the Vulgar with the greateſt ſcorn and cruelty. But when <hi>Eutropius</hi> fled to the Altar, <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> was in the Church; <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſeeing <hi>Eutropius</hi> lying there, and hearing the Souldiers and People cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, deliver us <hi>Eutropius,</hi> deliver us <hi>Eutropi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> for <hi>Eutropius</hi> muſt die; he preſently ſpeaks to the people, and commands ſilence, for he would preach: he had a preſent tongue and mind, he could expreſs what he pleaſed in the moſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Eloquence and curious Language. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple eaſily acquieſced, for it might deſerve a <hi>Quaere</hi> whether they more deſired <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> Eloquence, or <hi>Eutropius</hi> his death. He begins his Sermon with an Invective againſt <hi>Eutropius,</hi> and upbraids him with that injury that he did the Church of God. The Church, againſt whom he exerciſed hoſtility, imbraced him with open arms; the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar now was his Sanctuary, from which he had taken away the priviledge of protection; the Altar which is glorious in its own ſplendour, became more illuſtrious by that Lion lying bound at the feet of it. The Theatres, which he had enriched with many Offices and endowments, had betrayed and deſtroyed him; but the Church and Altar, to which he was a profeſſed enemy, relieved and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him; that he had formerly reproved his
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:132826:36"/> Pride and Inſolence, and had told him that his Dignity and Riches were fugitive Servants, that they would forſake and ruine him; but now his ſafety and happineſs were the Church and Altar of God. This would ſeem to argue in <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> a great pride, arrogance and cruelty, to throw ſuch diſgraces and ſcorns upon miſerable <hi>Eutropi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> but that was not <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> deſign, for in that ſame invective, he profeſſed, he ſpoke it for the benefit and favour of <hi>Eutropius;</hi> for turning himſelf to the People, with the like paſſionate Eloquence moves the People to the commiſerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Eutropius,</hi> prevails upon them. What by his conſtancy and courage, and his vaſt Eloquence, he ſo far prevailed that <hi>Eutropius</hi> was not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered into the hands of the Souldiers, till the Emperour had ſworn that <hi>Eutropius</hi> ſhould not be put to death. Thus that Golden ſhower of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, laid the Tempeſt of the Popular and Court fury.</p>
            <p>Though <hi>Valens</hi> was the great perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor <note place="margin">Their great Loyalty and Allegiance to their Prince.</note> of the Orthodox Chriſtians, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of the honour due to our bleſſed Lord and Saviour, yet <hi>Baſil</hi> never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the Chriſtians to reſiſt by Arms; and the protection of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> intimates the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of Chriſtians to their Governours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> though he was ſo dreadfully perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Empreſſes indignation againſt him, yet in his Sermons would praiſe the Emperour as the moſt holy and religious Prince. And when the Emperour was in danger of the <hi>Gothiſh</hi> Army, he
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:132826:36"/> ſtopt the fury of their Arms by his Eloquence and Piety, as appears by this ſubſequent Narrative. <hi>Gaynas,</hi> a <hi>Goth</hi> of the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereſie, fell from ſerving his own Prince, to the ſervice of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperour; under whom he performed great and proſperous Atchievements, hugely advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to that Empire; but receiving ſome diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments and diſgraces from <hi>Rufinus,</hi> the prime Miniſter of State, declined to <hi>Tribigildus</hi> the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiſh</hi> King, under whom he brought the <hi>Gothiſh</hi> Army into <hi>Thrace,</hi> and waſted the greateſt part of <hi>Greece;</hi> which forced the Emperour to unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Capitulations with him. The Peace being concluded, <hi>Gaynas</hi> comes to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and there is proclamed General of the Emperours Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; after which, he confidently demands the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of a Church for the <hi>Arrian</hi> Hereticks. <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> durſt not deny that, which was rather a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, then a Petition; therefore he ſends for <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> and communicates to him the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of <hi>Gaynas;</hi> to which <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> replyed, that he was totally averſe from ſuch a conceſſion, and prayed the Emperour, that he might confer with <hi>Gaynas,</hi> whom he queſtioned not but he ſhould either ſatisfie, or deter from the farther proſecuting of ſuch a deſign. <hi>Gaynas</hi> and <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> diſputed the reaſonableneſs of the demand; <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> totally denies it; he adds the ſervices he had done the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire; to which <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> ſaid, that nothing merits the turning the Place, wherein God is honoured with Praiſes and Hallelujahs, into a place wherein the Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:132826:37"/> is blaſphemed: And further adds, that he ought to remember that the honour done him by the Emperour was ſuperiour to his merits; and how different was his eſtate, from that condition he was in, when in the head of few Troops he paſſed the <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. Gaynas,</hi> confounded with his courage and reaſon, deſiſted; yet again attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſeizing of the Emperour, and deſtroying of <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> He was fruſtrated from thoſe deſigns by the miraculous power of God. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he flies to <hi>Tribigilaus</hi> the <hi>Gothiſh</hi> King, who received him with the higheſt reſpect; and commiſſioned him, in the head of an Army, to make a dreadful invaſion upon the <hi>Graecian</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; which filled <hi>Aſia</hi> with horrour and bloud, <hi>Greece</hi> it ſelf trembling under his Arms The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour was not provided to repel ſo great a force; whereupon <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> is ſent in an Embaſſie to that Barbarian, who though he knew the affront he had given him at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> yet under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes the buſineſs; <hi>Gaynas</hi> meets him with the greateſt kindneſs, and gives him the higheſt teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of reſpect; <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſo far prevails, that he affrights him from a further progreſs; whereby the Emperour had leiſure to raiſe ſuch an Army, which chaſtiſed the treachery and inſolence of <hi>Gaynas,</hi> and made him ſatisfie for all the injuries he had done to the <hi>Romans,</hi> in the ruine of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and the loſs of his life. Oh the glory of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion! that an unarmed perſon could free the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Empire from thoſe dangers, from which their own weapons could not preſerve them! ſo in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:132826:37"/> Spiritual Preaching, the verity of Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is aſſerted. The weapons of our warfare are not Carnal, but Spiritual through God. That one Biſhop ſhould more prevail over the enemies of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, then whole Armies! and when the City of <hi>Constantinople</hi> would have twice hindred his baniſhment, and would have oppoſed their Arms to the Emperours Edict, that commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and bloud might be hindred, he privately delivered himſelf into the hands of the Emperours Souldiers, who ſecretly conveyed him into exile: Nay when <hi>Innocentius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> would have pronounced a ſentence of Excommunication againſt the Emperour, and <hi>Honorins</hi> the Weſtern Emperour in the defence of <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> would have drawn down his Army to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> againſt <hi>Arcadius,</hi> he hindred the intentions of both, by his Eloquence, peaceable and quiet Letters. And to ſhew, he retained not a rancour againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour and Empreſs, or his other Court or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical enemies at <hi>Cucuſum,</hi> where he had a ſpace to breath in; he wrote that incomparable and excellent piece, ſtiled, <hi>No man is hurt but by himſelf.</hi> This is the glory of Chriſtanity, to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile the fear of God, and honour of the King to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. They muſt not rifle their duty, and yet they muſt not draw the Sword againſt their Princes. The foundation laid by a late Philoſopher of making the Princes will, the rule of Juſtice and goodneſs, for the preſervation of Government and the peace of Societies, overthrows the whole ſtructure of Religion, deſtroys the ſociety and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:132826:38" rendition="simple:additions"/> order of men, and is contradictory to the reaſon of men. But to ſecure Government and peace by Non-reſiſtance and Paſſive obedience, as it's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to Divine pleaſure, ſo it ſecures Religion, maintains Juſtice, and is the moſt certain defence of the Imperial power.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> privately retiring into <note place="margin">The Accident that happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi>
               </note> baniſhment, the People for ſome hours were ignorant that he had taken Ship for <hi>Armenia;</hi> but no ſooner the news was ſpread in the City, but it was fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with confuſion, terrours and cryes. Men, Women, and Children of all ſorts and qualities ran to the Haven, and there cry out, <hi>the Biſhop, the Biſhop is gone.</hi> They enquired of the Mariners where the laſt ſtep was, that they might kiſs the very impreſſion of his foot. Never City was more doleful then <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was then. The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the City, <hi>Optatus,</hi> was a Pagan, a zealous profeſſor of Idolatry; he, with the greateſt joy, embraced the baniſhment of <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> as an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion put into his hands to proſecute the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, with as great a cruelty and rage as ever the Heathen Tyrants did; to make a Chriſtian Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour by his hands the cauſe of inflicting as dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful tortures on them, as a <hi>Decius</hi> or <hi>Diocleſian.</hi> The Baniſhment of <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> happened imediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before <hi>Easter,</hi> the great Ternary of days; the days of our Lords being in the Grave, was the time when theſe Tragedies were acted. For then the Churches were filled with Chriſtians of all ſorts, many Men and Women were then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:132826:38"/> for Baptiſm to be celebated on <hi>Easter-day,</hi> the Deaconeſſes attending upon the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the Deacons upon the Men, in their diſtinct and ſeveral places; all which were filled with ſorrow for <hi>Chryſostom:</hi> incredible was their grief for the Decree of Baniſhment, fervent were their prayers for his continuance. <hi>Optatus</hi> commands his Troops to enter the Church, the people cry for <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> the Souldiers anſwer their Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with their Swords. Thus the Holy Church, the Sacred Altar, was beſmeared with bloud in the day of the Lords Paſſion. They enter the places where the <hi>Catechumens</hi> were; to the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men they offer the baſeſt indignities and cruelties; to the Men, all which malice and rage could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate. The Fonts were not now filled with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but bloud; and they, who were prepared to be conſecrated to God in the waters of Baptiſm, are now indeed baptized into the Baptiſm that Chriſt was baptized with. Oh dreadful paſſage! what, if <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> had been in ſome words indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, muſt the Flock of Chriſt thus ſuffer? and the Chriſtian Emperour give authority for ſuch an indignity to be offered to Chriſtian Religion? The Souldiers, after they had wounded the <hi>Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens,</hi> poured their bloud into the Fonts; ſtript the Women naked; and in a barbarous cruelty and diveliſh rage againſt Chriſtianity, (for theſe were Pagan Troops) in a ſcorn dipt them in their own bloud, and cruelly murthered many of them. Who can read without tears ſuch a Tragedy, done in a Chriſtian City, with the Authority of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:132826:39"/> Emperour, on the day of our bleſſed Lord's Paſſion? but O Eternal God! thy ways are a great depth, and cannot be ſearched out:</p>
            <p>In the very night that <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> was carried into Exile, a Fire began in the Throne of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> which conſumed that ſtately Cathedral, wherein he conſtantly Preached: the flames being carried by a violent Eaſt-wind, lighted upon the Palace of the Senators of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> the Common-Council-houſe of the City, a rare Pile of buildings, and laid it level with the ground. Thoſe flames were matter of Joy to <hi>Optatus,</hi> another oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity being preſented to him for the reaking his malice upon the Chriſtians. The favourites of <hi>Chryſostom</hi> were preſently clapt in priſon, and laid in Irons, eſpecially the Presbyters and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, who were faithful to him; the <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan</hi> Ladies not being ſpared, many of whom were put to cruel Torments, that the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Hiſtorian judges it beſt to paſs by the Narrative in ſilence. But in all the Tortures that they ſuffer'd, neither man nor woman confeſſed the Fact, but utterly denied it. <hi>Olympias</hi> a great Lady, the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Nebridius</hi> a rich Conſul, embraced a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious life; She was a great admirer and lover of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> her Eſtate was crime enough, ſhe is drag'd to the Tribunal, accuſed as an Accomplice in the burning of the Church: to which accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe bravely anſwers, That there could be no pretext of reaſon that ſhe ſhould endeavour the conſuming of a Sacred Aedifice, when ſhe had ſpent vaſt ſums of money in the building of many;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:132826:39"/> but neither a great Fine laid on her, nor the Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſhe then endured, could any whit diminiſh her affections to that Excellent Preacher; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards having liberty given her by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, ſhe retired to <hi>Macedonia,</hi> and there in ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and Piety ſpent the reſt of her moſt glorious life. Some attribute the Fire to the favourers of <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> but certainly the Tortures and Racks, that were inflicted on them, would have extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from one or other a confeſſion; however they, who in all their actions diſcovered that they had rather die then ſin, would not have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in a notorious lie. Others attributed it to a Miracle, as thinking without praeternatural po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, the flame could not, out of the Throne, catch the roof of the Temple, and without a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine deſignation could not have flown over ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny houſes of the City, and at ſuch a diſtance, prey only upon the Senators Palace. To deny the more peculiar and miraculous operations of God, is an unpardonable Blaſphemy; but to believe every narration, is childiſh credulity; and to make every thing that ſeems ſtrange to require a ſupernatural cauſe, argues ignorance and ſuperſtition. It ſeems the moſt probable, that the Heathens were the occaſion of that conflagration, that there might be an occaſion given to the Heathen Governour to inflict all ſorts of puniſhments upon the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. For under the pretence of carrying <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> into Baniſhment, and to diſperſe the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians conventions, they ſeized upon the Church, and ſo might juſtly be reputed the Authors of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:132826:40"/> that fact. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> being baniſhed, <hi>Arſatius</hi> (aged 80 years, a man of no Learning, nor Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) the meaneſt and ſillieſt perſon, ſucceeds the greateſt and moſt Eloquent perſon in the World. Every where the Chriſtians and Religious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons meeting <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> received him with all kindneſs, filled the Air with theſe Acclamations, <hi>Let the Sun rather ceaſe to ſhine, then not</hi> Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom <hi>preach.</hi> In his journey to <hi>Armenia,</hi> the place deſigned for his baniſhment, he met with extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary difficulties, oft-times in danger of the <hi>Iſaurian</hi> Robbers. The Souldiers that guarded him, had in Commiſſion that they ſhould tire him with continued Journeys; for he was reduced to great weakneſs, and mightily obnoxious to Feavers, by reaſon of his great Auſterities. But at length they arrived at <hi>Cucuſum,</hi> where the Biſhop of that place courteouſly received him, and had the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of peace and quietneſs. To him there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted many of his Friends from <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> out of <hi>Armenia, Syria, Aſia, Cappadocia,</hi> and the Countries bordering upon the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea. Moſt of the Letters which are extant in his Works, which are brave Monuments of his Piety and Learning, were written in the time of his baniſhment. But the fame of his admirable piety in thoſe his great afflictions daily increaſing, and the love of the City every day haſtening towards him, cauſed the Emperour to prohibit any commerce of Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters with him. The time of his baniſhment he continually ſpent in Prayers and Preachings, if his Guard permitted him any liberty of reſt. The
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:132826:40"/> People, from the bordering Nations and remote Countries, undertaking the dangerous and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Journeys to hear the Eloquence of this great Perſon.</p>
            <p>That perſon or Court, to whom the <note place="margin">The Appeals of theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>
               </note> laſt Appeal is made, is unqueſtionably inveſted with a ſupreme Authority. <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine, de Rom. Pont. lib. 2. cap.</hi> 29. argues for the <hi>Roman</hi> Primacy from Appeals; averring, that it was the cuſtom of the Univerſal Church, to tender her final Addreſſes to the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop; which muſt neceſſarily prove that the Church did acknowledge the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Biſhop to be her ſupreme Head: he takes no cognizance of <hi>Baſils</hi> Embaſſie to the Weſt, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legdeth <hi>Chryſostoms</hi> Letters to <hi>Innocent. Baronius ad An. Dom.</hi> 371, 372 doth endeavour to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the Papal Primacy from the Letters of <hi>Baſil</hi> to <hi>Damaſus,</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Rome. Barboſa</hi> a late Canoniſt, 2 <hi>diſtinct. cauſ. 10. queſt. 3. cap. Cuncta per mundum,</hi> this boldly blaſphemes: He aſſerts, <hi>'Tis an errour in the Faith, to ſay that an Appeal lies from the Pope to God himſelf. For when the ſupreme Prieſt is the Vicar of our Lord Jeſus here upon Earth, his Conſistory is the ſame with that of Christ; they therefore think Heretically, who believe that they may Appeal from the definitive ſentence of the Pope, to Chriſt; as though the Tribunal of Chriſt and the Pope were not the ſame.</hi> Who wonders at the impious confidence of Paraſites? <hi>Lipſius</hi> a Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, abhorred ſuch ſentiments; when the Maſter of the Hoſpitallers was by the inſtigation of <hi>Philip</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:132826:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Fair of <hi>France,</hi> condemned to be burnt by Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban,</hi> he made his Appeal to Heaven, and cited them both to appear before the Tribunal of Chriſt within the ſpace of a year: in the compaſs of which time, the Pope and <hi>French</hi> King both died, to give an account, as <hi>Lipſius</hi> thinks, of their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and injuſtices before the great Judge of the World: <hi>Lipſii Mon. Pol.</hi> I intend not a full diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion of this Topick, but clearly to manifeſt that neither of theſe Fathers acknowledged the Papal Supremacy. <hi>Baſil</hi> never directs his Epiſtles to the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, but to the Weſtern Biſhops, Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marine Biſhops, or to the Biſhops of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>France.</hi> The occaſions of which Epiſtles, was the Perſecutions and great diſturbances that the Eaſtern Church ſuffered by the fury of the <hi>Arrians.</hi> Whilſt the Weſtern Church flouriſhed in proſperity and peace, the inſcription of one of his Epiſtles is thus, <hi>To our Brethren and Biſhops in the West.</hi> How can it be imagined, if this great man believed the Papal Supremacy, that he would ſo direct his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters? We charge the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> with Innovations, they require the time in which thoſe Innovations were introduc'd; they charge the <hi>Greek</hi> Church with Schiſm, we may enquire, when that Church acknowledgeth the <hi>Roman</hi> Juriſdiction, and when the Schiſm of <hi>Greeks</hi> commenced. <hi>Baſil</hi> when the Eaſt was ſo dreadfully tormented by the Orthodox Biſhop, was choſen by reaſon of the greatneſs of his Learning, and fineneſs of his Pen, to be their Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, at whoſe inſtigation he in their names wrote to the Weſtern Biſhops, and ſent three ſeveral Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſies,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:132826:41"/> to none of which he received any anſwer; this neglect caſt him into a juſt paſſion in his Letter to <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Samoſatum,</hi> he thus writes; <hi>What help can be expected from the ſuperciliouſneſs of the Weſt? for they neither know the truth, nor will endure to learn it; for being poſſeſſed with falſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices, they act the ſame things they formerly did in the caſe of</hi> Marcellus; <hi>by their ambitious conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding againſt thoſe which publickly maintain the truth, they themſelves give a confirmation of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie. I my ſelf do intend to write to the chiefeſt of them, but not in uſual manner, in the name of my fellow Biſhops. I will not mention any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Eccleſiaſtical affairs, only I will acquaint them, that they neither will know the truth by us, nor will entertain thoſe means by which they may know it; and that on no account ought they to inſult over thoſe who are oppreſſed by afflictions: neither ought they to eſteem Pride to be Honour and Dignity, a ſin which of it ſelf is ſufficient to render a perſon odious unto God.</hi> How is it poſſible to imagine that theſe expreſſions are conſiſtent with St. <hi>Baſils</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the <hi>Roman</hi> Primacy or Infallibility? can he think thoſe to be infallible, whom he ſays neither know the truth, nor will uſe means to know it? Did he believe <hi>Damaſus</hi> to be the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Biſhop, whom he calls the chiefeſt of them, that is, of the Weſtern Biſhops, not of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church? <hi>Baronius</hi> to this anſwers, <hi>Good men are ſometimes tranſported with paſſion, but they afterwards reduce themſelves within the bounds of reaſon. For after this he expreſſeth his high eſteem
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:132826:42"/> he had of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and commends the purity, and rectitude of her Faith; by which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that he did not believe that Church Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and that Good men might condemn Pride with greater Pride; his beloved</hi> Nazianzen <hi>accuſeth him of that vice.</hi> Grant this, yet it will not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded, that <hi>Baſil</hi>'s Addreſſes could import his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the pretended Supremacy or Infallibility: he condemns not the Weſtern Biſhops for Hereſie, but for their ſtrengthning of Hereſie by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging of Hereticks; which they did, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving <hi>Marcellus</hi> into communion, whom the Eaſtern Church excommunicated. Good men may fall into paſſion; <hi>Baſil</hi> unqueſtionably had a juſt reaſon for his indignation; who can accuſe his anger? he in the name of the whole Eaſtern Church, then groaning under moſt dreadful Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions, writes three Epiſtles to the Weſtern Biſhops, who refuſed to return one Letter to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie their compaſſion. Did <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſuſpect <hi>Baſil</hi> of Pride? No: he knew him to be one of the humbleſt men in the World. <hi>Nazianzen</hi> was very unwilling to accept of <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which <hi>Baſil</hi> enforceth him thereunto; this kind and pious violence he calls pride. It is not unworthy to enquire the reaſon, why the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Church caſt ſuch a neglect upon the Eaſtern, and peculiarly upon <hi>Baſil</hi> their Secretary. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius</hi> aſſigns this, <hi>That</hi> Baſil <hi>and his Aſſociates were traduced as Hereticks; for though according to the</hi> Nicene <hi>Council, they acknowledged the Faith of one ſubſtance, yet by reaſon the</hi> Latine <hi>Church uſed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:132826:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> the word</hi> Perſona, <hi>to expreſs the diſtinction in the Trinity, and the</hi> Greek <hi>not condemning the</hi> Latines <hi>uſed the word</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the</hi> Latines <hi>that judged that to be of the ſame ſignification with</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>did think they were either</hi> Sabellians <hi>or</hi> Tritheits: <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which Calumny</hi> Baſil <hi>for a great while lay.</hi> Let this be yielded, what to the purpoſe? <hi>Damaſus</hi> entertained this unjuſt ſuſpicion; <hi>Baſil</hi> by many Letters and Apologies vindicates himſelf; at laſt clears himſelf of that Cloud; ſatisfies the Weſtern Biſhops; they acknowledging, that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Greek</hi> language, and the Eaſtern Church, that <hi>Perſona</hi> in the <hi>Latine,</hi> did properly denote the diſtinction in the Trinity. Where is the infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? how came it paſs that an infallible Judge was ignorant of the meaning of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? but is there no other reaſon then that? He in his Epiſtles to the Tranſmarine Biſhops, ſaith, <hi>A great deſire of waiting upon you poſſeſſes me, but a continual ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs impedes. I have a long time expected, to ſee if you would have any care of us. If you condemn us before we are heard, and convicted, we ſhall not at all be injured; only we ſhall loſe Chriſtian love and charity, which you will make us believe you have not: be not hearers of Calumnies, but tryers of the Truth; let not ſuch reaſons prevail with you; we want not the help of others, we need not the Communion of others. God that ſeparated Iſlands from Continents, unites the Inhabitants by love. Brethren, nothing can divide us, if our own choice and proper motion makes not the ſeparation. If you account your ſelves head of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, the head cannot ſay to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:132826:43"/> the feet, I have no need of thee; but if you rank your ſelves amongst the Members of the Church, ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay to us; we have no need of you. We earneſtly ſeek an union in the ſame opinion, we paſſionately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat your prayers. The very Heathens who know not the true God, deſire prayers, they combine toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for their mutual aſſiſtance; are not we aſhamed of ſeparation? are we diſpoſed to ſuffer ſo great an injury?</hi> Can theſe lines admit of <hi>Roman</hi> Primacy? durſt <hi>Baſil,</hi> if he had received ſuch ſentiments, propoſe that Dilemma, either you are the Head, or Members? and may not we reaſonably judge, that <hi>Damaſus</hi> was nettled at the inſcription of the Letters? 'Tis evident, that the Eaſtern Biſhops did not Appeal to the Weſtern, as to their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious; they deſire their prayers, the manifeſting their conſent in the ſame Doctrine with them, and give what aſſiſtance they can to them. Take it from their own Letters; <hi>To our Brethren and Biſhops in the West. How gracious is God, who min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles joy with our ſorrows? we have received com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort by thoſe Letters which</hi> Athanaſius <hi>ſent to us from you; he witneſſeth the integrity and ſoundneſs of your Faith, which demonstrate your commendable union and concord with us. God hath comforted us by</hi> Sabellius, <hi>our Reverend fellow Deacon, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints us with thoſe excellent things that he ſaw in your Church; and he knowing by his own experience the miſerable eſtate of ours, he paſſionately intreateth you, that with fervent and inceſſant prayers, you would contend with God for us.</hi> All which intimates nothing of Primacy: This is not an Appeal to
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:132826:43"/> proper Judges, but an addreſs for Brotherly aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. In another Epiſtle; <hi>We have earneſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, and aloud begged for the manifeſting your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to us, by giving us aſſistance, and ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thizing with us: but ye have not appeared in our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, we moſt earneſtly deſiring, O moſt Reverend, to ſignifie our confuſions to the Weſtern Emperour; If that be difficult, ſend from you to us, to viſit and comfort us, who are ſo grievouſly afflicted, that you your ſelves may be the ſpectators of the Eaſt; Words are not able to expreſs our Calamities.</hi> Here is no acknowledgement of a Juriſdiction: no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding man can ever be brought to believe, that the Author of ſuch Letters ſubmitted to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of them to whom they were directed. But <hi>Baronius</hi> ſays, <hi>That the Appeals of</hi> Euſtachius <hi>and</hi> Marcellus <hi>to</hi> Rome, <hi>perſpicuouſly evince the</hi> Roman <hi>Primacy. Euſtachius</hi> was a light and unconſtant perſon, after he had ſubſcribed and profeſſed the Faith of one ſubſtance: he relapſed into <hi>Arria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm,</hi> for which he was excommunicated. St. <hi>Baſil</hi> to the Weſtern Biſhops gives this account of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius.</hi> He was Biſhop of <hi>Sebastia,</hi> of the lower <hi>Armenia,</hi> who very much moleſted the Church; at <hi>Alexandria</hi> he was inſtructed by <hi>Arrius,</hi> and eſteemed one of his chiefeſt Diſciples; he returns to his own Country; for his impious opinion, by <hi>Hermogenes</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> was excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated; but afterwards, preſenting to him a confeſſion of his ſound Faith, was reſtored and ordained. He relapſed, and was again excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated at <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> returning into his
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:132826:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> own Country, he preſented a form of ſound Faith, whereupon he was received and made Biſhop after that, in the Synod of <hi>Ancira;</hi> he anathematized the Faith of one ſubſtance; his Hereſie he promoted in <hi>Cilicia,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> whereupon in a Synod at <hi>Melitina</hi> he was depoſed, for which he makes his addreſs to the Weſtern Biſhops; before <hi>Liberius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> he makes a confeſſion of the true Faith, ſubſcribes it; by him, and the Weſtern Biſhops, he was abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; from whom he received Letters to a Synod met at <hi>Tiana,</hi> to receive him into the Church, and reſtore him into his Biſhoprick, which by them was performed. All this is granted; but the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy not granted. It's evident that St. <hi>Baſil</hi> wrote not only to <hi>Liberius,</hi> but to the Weſtern Biſhops. And what was done by the Eaſtern Biſhops, was not only upon the account of <hi>Liberius,</hi> but of the other Weſtern Biſhops. It was a cuſtom in the Church, to certifie one another of their agreement in the form of ſound Doctrine, and of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who were Hereticks and Excommunicated, whereby there might be no communion held with ſuch perſons; it was uſual with theſe, to make their Addreſs to other Churches, that they might receive them into Communion with them, and by that means to receive Letters Teſtimonial of the integrity of their Faith, the revoking of their Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and their deſire that they might be reſtored into the Church, from whence they were excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated; which was oft performed. All this did not include any Authority, but a Fraternal
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:132826:44"/> love, and communion; that they agreeing in the ſame Faith, the perſons whom they received into communion, ſhould be of the ſame Faith with them; whereupon, if any Heretick excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated by his own Biſhop, addreſſed himſelf to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church, with whom his Biſhop was in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; and he there revoked his Hereſie, and made profeſſion of the Catholick Faith, he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into communion; and having obtained <hi>literas format as,</hi> with a Copy of his Faith, he was many times reſtored into Communion. This is every where obvious in Eccleſiaſtical hiſtory. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtachius</hi> being excommunicated, flies to the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Biſhops. <hi>Baſil</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Weſtern Biſhops concerning <hi>Eustachius, Apollinaris,</hi> and <hi>Paulinus,</hi> thinking he ſhould be reſtored by them, by whom he was received and carried Letters from them to us, to the Synod of <hi>Tyana,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the profeſſion of his Faith, and the deſire of his reſtauration; which was performed; the Synod reſtored him. <hi>Liberius</hi> perſwaded, it very much conduced to the peace of the Church, for to agree in the ſame Faith; it tended much to the confuſion of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> to ſee the Eaſt and Weſt conſpiring in the Orthodox Faith; the beſt and greateſt part of Chriſtians to be their enemies. <hi>Eustachius</hi> being very inconſtant, ſometimes did publickly profeſs the Faith, ſometimes propagate Hereſie; where he did this, he was excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated; where the other, he was abſolved. And in that very place where he was condemned, if he revoked his errours, the condemnation was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:132826:45"/> This ſame <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> after he had been convicted of Hereſie, addreſſes himſelf to St. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil;</hi> before whom he makes a confeſſion of the true Faith, and ſubſcribes a confeſſion which <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> himſelf drew up; upon which he was received into communion. The ſame is to be averred con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the actions of <hi>Liberius,</hi> and the Weſtern Biſhops, in the caſe of <hi>Euſtachius. Baſil</hi> therefore earneſtly intreats them, that ſince they lived at ſo great a diſtance, they would believe nothing, but what they received from thoſe perſons, who lived in the Eaſt, and were worthy of credit: therefore he gives them a Character of <hi>Euſtachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> after his reſtauration; he now deſtroys that Faith on the account of which he was reſtored into communion, he joyns himſelf with them who anathematized the Faith of one ſubſtance, and is become the Ring-leader of the <hi>Pneumato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mici;</hi> he uſeth the confidence you gave him, to the ruine of many: ſince from you, he took a liberty to injure the Church, 'tis neceſſary, that from you proceed a redreſs; and therefore that you would give an account to us, for what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he was received into communion, and why he is now changed; and wherefore he enervates that favour granted him by the Fathers. In all which there is not the leaſt intimation of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy. That which was the cauſe of his reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was a form of ſound Faith, which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully preſented to the Weſtern Biſhops, which with their Letters he tenders to the Synod of <hi>Tiana,</hi> upon which by the Authority of the Synod he was reſtored.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:132826:45"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> (as I have before rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Weſtern Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</note> having incurred the Empreſſes diſpleaſure; <hi>Arcadius</hi> the Emperour ſendeth for <hi>Theophilus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> to come to <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> who, upon the Emperours com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, attended with ſeveral other Biſhops, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at <hi>Constantinople.</hi> He calleth a Synod, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the Accuſation exhibited againſt <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom,</hi> whom he ſummoneth before him. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom</hi> refuſeth to appear; whereupon he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for contumacy, pronounced guilty, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, depoſed, and by the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Emperour baniſhed. Upon which, he writeth to <hi>Innocent,</hi> bitterly complaining of the notorious injury done to him, and of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Church; and paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately intreateth, that he and the Weſtern Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops would afford him what aſſiſtance they could, and uſe all poſſible endeavours they could, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs thoſe grievances, with which that Church was afflicted. That this is an Appeal to <hi>Rome,</hi> as to a ſupreme Court of Judicature, is averred by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and others; but that it is not, appears thus: <hi>Baronius</hi> ſaith, <hi>That</hi> Theophilus <hi>as he was Archbiſhop of</hi> Alexandria, <hi>had power over the Churches of</hi> Greece, <hi>and therefore might legally ſummon</hi> Chryſoſtom <hi>before him.</hi> An aſſertion which I cannot but wonder at: for what Authority can the Archbiſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> have over the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Constantinople?</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> to <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius</hi> accuſeth him of unjuſt uſurpation; <hi>'Tis
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:132826:46"/> not congruous,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that one out of</hi> Aegypt, (meaning <hi>Theophilus) ſhould judge thoſe that lived in</hi> Thrace. Which manifeſtly renounceth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Authority of <hi>Theophilus. Arcadius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour then keeping his Court at <hi>Pera,</hi> a City in <hi>Theſſalonia, Theophilus</hi> with his Aſſociate Biſhops attended him: the Emperour iſſueth out his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> that he ſhould appear at <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> before <hi>Theophilus,</hi> to anſwer thoſe crimes that were objected againſt him; he refuſeth in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Innocent;</hi> he giveth this reaſon, 'tis not fit for any perſon to appear before a Foreign Court of Judicature; and that all things that are acted, ought to be tryed within their own Juriſdiction; all things ought to be examined within their own Province, before their proper Court, to whom the cognizance of the Cauſe doth belong: which is an undoubted teſtimony againſt Foreign Appeals. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> could not poſſibly think, that an Appeal to <hi>Rome</hi> was neceſſary, ſince upon the account before-recited, he refuſed to appear at <hi>Pera:</hi> withall he Appeals to a General Council, he acquainteth <hi>Innocent,</hi> that he was not guilty, and could wholly free himſelf from thoſe crimes laid to his charge; but that he would not appear before incompetent Judges, an unlawful Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which conſiſted of his profeſſed and impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable enemies, but that he would appear before a General Council, where in the preſence of 1000 Biſhops he could manifeſt his Innocency. By which it is evident, he Appealed not to <hi>Rome,</hi> but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed himſelf to the Weſtern Biſhops; that as
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:132826:46"/> much as in them lay, they would endeavour that a General Council might be called; before whom he might appear, all grievances redreſſed, and Peace to the Church reſtored. And, that it was not an Appeal to <hi>Rome,</hi> appeareth by the Epiſtle it ſelf: for though the title be to <hi>Innocent</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet in the body of the Epiſtle, we find that he addreſſeth himſelf to the Biſhops of the Weſt, whom he calls moſt Reverend, and moſt Holy Biſhops. Farther to evince that the <hi>Greek</hi> Church did not acknowledge the <hi>Roman</hi> Primacy, we muſt attend to what <hi>Phocius</hi> averrs; <hi>Innocent,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>laboured much on the behalf of</hi> John, <hi>but all in vain; he fent his</hi> Apocriſarii, <hi>who were injuriouſly treated, and ſcornfully ſent back; and what prayers ſo ever he uſed, were to no purpoſe.</hi> The perſons to whom the Letters and Meſſengers of <hi>Innocent</hi> were ſent, were undoubtedly the Emperour, <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus,</hi> and the reſt of the Holy Biſhops. If ſo, this fact muſt needs manifeſt the opinion they had of the <hi>Roman</hi> Primacy. That neither St. <hi>Baſil</hi> nor St. <hi>Chryſostom</hi> did believe the <hi>Roman</hi> Primacy, the caſe of <hi>Miletius</hi> and <hi>Paulinus</hi> evidently declares. <hi>Miletius</hi> was thought to be an <hi>Arrian,</hi> he was Biſhop of <hi>Sebaſtia</hi> in <hi>Armenia: Eudoxius</hi> the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> being dead, he was by the <hi>Arrians</hi> tranſlated from <hi>Sebaſtia</hi> to <hi>Antioch:</hi> (then in every City of the Eaſt, every Sect of Chriſtians in it had its peculiar Biſhop; when <hi>Eudoxius</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned the <hi>Arrian</hi> Church in <hi>Antioch,</hi> the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Chriſtians had <hi>Euſtachius</hi> for their Biſhop.) The <hi>Antiochian Arrians</hi> hearing that <hi>Miletius</hi> was
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:132826:47"/> a perſon of a ſingular life, and of very great Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, and that he was once of the ſame opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with them, they judged, that the opinion the World had of this Perſon, would be a means to draw to their Party the Inhabitants of <hi>Antioch.</hi> There was ſo great a ſame of him, that when he came to <hi>Antioch,</hi> multitudes of perſons went out to meet him; both thoſe which were followers of <hi>Arrius,</hi> and thoſe that were adherers to <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus.</hi> When he came firſt to <hi>Antioch,</hi> he preached publickly the moral Duties of Chriſtianity; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he publickly taught the Faith of one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. There was then a Synod: the Emperour commanded the Biſhops to give their opinion: After <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Laodicea</hi> had moſt heretically de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, and <hi>Acaſius</hi> of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> had not ſo blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly, but not truly and Apoſtolically de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered his, <hi>Miletius</hi> was commanded to make a profeſſion of his Faith; he, contrary to the opinions of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> according to the <hi>Nicene</hi> decree, gave his belief with a great deal of exactneſs and truth; upon which by the inſtigation of the <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> he was baniſhed. <hi>Euſtachius,</hi> who from <hi>Perea</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> was tranſlated to <hi>Antioch,</hi> a perſon fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for conſtancy, ſoundneſs in the Faith and Religion, was baniſhed in the time of <hi>Conſtantius. Paulinus</hi> a Presbyter of <hi>Antioch;</hi> governed the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church in <hi>Antioch;</hi> thoſe of the people that were ſound in the Faith, notwithſtanding the endeavours of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> he retained and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the Catholick Doctrine. The Biſhops of the Church that were baniſhed under <hi>Julian</hi> the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:132826:47"/> Emperour, being reſtored, endeavoured to apply fit remedies for the redreſſing the diſorders of the Church. <hi>Lucifer</hi> a Biſhop of <hi>Sardinia,</hi> taking to himſelf two other Biſhops, ordained <hi>Paulinus</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Antioch. Miletius</hi> being by the Emperour <hi>Gratian</hi> recalled from Exile, went to <hi>Antioch</hi> to take poſſeſſion of his See; <hi>Paulinus,</hi> though or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained after <hi>Miletius,</hi> would remain Shepherd of his own Flock, and Biſhop of <hi>Antioch: Miletius</hi> would not forſake that honour which his Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conferred on him; nor ought he do it; for he was pre-ordained, and was a perſon of that holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that he judged his office of more concern to him, then his dignity. This was the great calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that in a City in which there were ſo many evil opinions, to the encouraging of Hereſie, two Catholick Biſhops ſhould contend one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: both were excellent perſons, both of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable fame; what cauſe ſhould be aſſigned of their diviſions? both of them appeared, by Characters given by excellent Hiſtorians, to be very holy perſons; the Eaſtern ſided with <hi>Miletius,</hi> the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Church with <hi>Paulinus:</hi> perhaps there were heats and animoſities, failings to which retired and ſevere perſons are obnoxious. May I give a conjecture, which may give ſome juſtification of them both: <hi>Miletius</hi> advanced to the See of <hi>Antioch</hi> by the <hi>Arrians</hi> themſelves, when he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered himſelf to be of a contrary opinion; his Holineſs, Learning and Eloquence, converted many of the <hi>Arrians;</hi> theſe would never forſake him, who was the inſtrument of their converſion.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:132826:48" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Paulinus</hi> after the baniſhment of <hi>Euſtachius</hi> being conſtant in the Faith, continuing in <hi>Antioch</hi> admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the holy office to the Faithful, he ſo obliged him, that they would never forſake him. Withall, his adherents were offended with <hi>Miletius,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was ordained by <hi>Arrians. Miletius</hi> was of ſo ſweet a temper, as he proffer'd amicable terms of reconciliation. Let what will be ſaid, that can be ſaid in favour of <hi>Paulinus, Miletius</hi> had the better cauſe; and the ſuffrage of the Weſtern Church in his behalf, doth make it fully appear that the Weſtern Biſhops refuſed the <hi>Roman</hi> Primacy. The <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhop, and the Weſt, took the part of <hi>Paulinus:</hi> the <hi>Grecian</hi> Biſhops, and thoſe of the Eaſt, that of <hi>Miletius.</hi> If that the Eaſtern Church did believe the Primacy, how durſt they maintain that Biſhop which was not approved by the <hi>Roman?</hi> It was againſt the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Canons, that two Biſhops ſhould be in the ſame Church: and yet there were two Catholick Biſhops in <hi>Antioch;</hi> one approved by the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern, the other by the Eaſtern Church. <hi>Miletius</hi> was a man of moſt ſingular Piety, and of equal meekneſs; he converſing with <hi>Paulinus,</hi> thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaks him. <hi>When our Sheep are at union, they feed in the ſame common Pasture, and we contend about the right of governing of them. Let us leave off our quarrelling, and live in mutual concord: If I die be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, be you the only Paſtor of the Sheep; If God ſhall call you hence before me, then to the utmoſt of my power, and with my greateſt care I will govern the Church of God.</hi> This moderate propoſal, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pores</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:132826:48"/> one of <hi>Gratians</hi> Generals (who had in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from that Emperour, to thruſt all the <hi>Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> out of the Churches, and to reſtore the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Catholicks) being at <hi>Antioch,</hi> ſeeing this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention, and knowing both of them to be Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and yet ſeeing the moderation of <hi>Miletius,</hi> confirm'd him in the government of his Churches, who met in the Suburbs; and <hi>Paulinus</hi> had a ſmall Church for his Adherents in the City. For the tranſlation of <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> a Synod was there convened, to which not <hi>Pauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> but <hi>Miletius</hi> was called; a ſufficient teſtimony of the Judgment of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Church: before the Synod was ended, <hi>Miletius</hi> died, infinitely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed, extraordinarily praiſed; all the learned Tongues and Pens were exerciſed in <hi>Panegyricks:</hi> his learning and vertues procured him ſo great a love and honour, that after his death they drew his Picture upon the Walls and Hangings; they cut it upon Rings, and engrav'd it on their Cups: his death cauſed the Council to tarry longer then they intended; for the <hi>Antiochians</hi> choſe <hi>Flavia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> his ſucceſſor, whom that Council confirmed in the See. <hi>Paulinus</hi> being dead, <hi>Evagrius</hi> was choſen his ſucceſſor by his party. <hi>Damaſus</hi> and the Weſtern Biſhops were very angry with the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Flavianus;</hi> they wrote to <hi>Theodoſius</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him; on the contrary <hi>Theodoſius</hi> defendeth and maintaineth his ordination, and aſſerteth, that all the Eaſt, all the <hi>Aſiatick</hi> and <hi>Pontick</hi> Churches, the Churches of <hi>Thrace,</hi> and all <hi>Illyrium,</hi> were the Patrons of the ordination of <hi>Flavianus.</hi> This <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vianus</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:132826:49"/> was that Biſhop ſent to <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> by reaſon of the ſedition of <hi>Antioch,</hi> on no account could he be moved by <hi>Damaſus,</hi> or the Weſt, to relinquiſh his Epiſcopal Authority. If the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> had an univerſal Primacy, how durſt the Eaſtern reject that Biſhop, whom the <hi>Pope</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and approve of him, whom the <hi>Pope</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected. This contention remained ſeveral years: the Catholick Chriſtians keeping divided meetings under diſtinct Biſhops, until one <hi>Alexander</hi> was conſtituted Biſhop of that See in the place of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrius,</hi> who was dead; he being famous for the admirableneſs of his life, Eloquence, contempt of the World, and many Heavenly vertues, what by his perſwaſions and labour, obtained his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended union in this diviſion. To what part did <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> adhere? to the part of <hi>Miletius. Baſil</hi> hugely commends him; by his Letters is ſeen the value he had of him, and affection for him: by him <hi>Chryſostom</hi> was ordained Deacon: in the commendation of him, after his death, he made a moſt excellent Sermon; and that he was of the Church of <hi>Flavianus,</hi> one of his Presbyters, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeareth by his Sermons <hi>ad Populum. Flavia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> being gone in an Embaſſie to <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> him he commendeth, and encourageth them on the account of the Excellency of their Archbiſhop. If <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> did believe the <hi>Roman</hi> Prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and made their Appeals to <hi>Damaſus</hi> and <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> as ſupreme heads of the Church, and final Judgers of controverſies, how could they take the parts of thoſe Biſhops whom the <hi>Popes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned?</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:132826:49"/>
            <p>There is certainly in man a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <note place="margin">The Heavenly-mindedneſs of theſe Fathers.</note> and immortal Soul; a Divine fire burns in his breaſt, from whence flow thoſe ſparks which mount higher and higher, until they aſcend to thoſe infinite and coeleſtial flames: There are reſtleſs paſſions in him, after a compleat felicity, which is fully diſcovered by our Lord and Saviour, the end of whoſe coming into the World was to promote the Divine Glory, and conduct men to Eternal happineſs. In his face ſhined the Glory of God; he had the words of Eternal life; by his Goſpel, Life and Immortality was brought to light; the genuine Diſciples of this Lord, muſt have their converſation in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, being as Pilgrims and Strangers in this World, they muſt demean themſelves as fellow Citizens of the Saints, and Houſhold of God. Excellently <hi>Nazianzen</hi> in his Apology; <hi>The Soul comes from God, and is Divine; for two reaſons it is united to the Body, a ſubstance of a worſe and lower allay:</hi> 1. That by this, ſhe fighting with the fleſh, and combating with thoſe paſſions which would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs her, ſhe might be crowned with glory: and this happens through that infinite love of God, who would, that Virtue and Happineſs ſhould not be the meer product of Nature, but it ſhould proceed from choice, and be the effect of the motions of a well regulating Will. 2. That ſhe might draw the body to her ſelf, raiſing it above this World, and in a ſhort ſpace freeing it from its weight and ponderouſneſs, may ſo prepare it, that what God is to the Soul, the Soul may be to the Body; that
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:132826:50"/> having poliſht by her own art and care this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy matter her Servant, ſhe might be united unto God. Of this their Heavenly-mindedneſs they gave three demonſtrations: 1. A ſincere and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect contempt of this World, and indeed that act of renunciation of this World, whereby their whole Eſtates renounced, and Poverty choſen, carries a thouſand reaſons with it. <hi>Baſil</hi> when young, retires into the <hi>Pontick</hi> Wilderneſs; the manner of his life he elegantly gives in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile to <hi>Gregorius:</hi> the purpoſe of his Soul, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted by the inſtitution of his life, fully evinced, that he had a ſmall value or eſteem for any thing in this World: for he aimed at that bleſſedneſs, which God had promiſed. Riches he had none, Pleaſures he diſregarded: thus he ſaith of himſelf. <hi>A contrite and humble mind, was always attended with a ſad and dejected Countenance. A negligent garb, horrid and ſtaring hair, ſordid Cloaths; ſuch which on purpoſe Mourners wear, I out of deſign and pure choice of my will do put on; a Girdle ties my garments to my body. The only end of my Cloaths, is a defence against the extremity of heat and cold: Meat, Bread and Herbs; Drink, Water; one hour towards the end of the day, is deſigned for a late Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; I ſleep leaning on a tree, not affording too much rest to my wearied body.</hi> No one that leads ſuch a manner of life can be judged, either to gape after riches, or indulge pleaſures. Did he affect Honour? No: The glory that he was ambitious of, was that Honour with God; a vein of Meekneſs and Humility runs through all his writing, he ſpeaks
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:132826:50"/> of himſelf with the greateſt Humility; he was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of aſpiring to the See of <hi>Neocaeſarea,</hi> but how unjuſtly, I manifeſted formerly. When Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, his humility endeared him to his Dioceſs, and terrified <hi>Valens</hi> and the <hi>Arrians. Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith of himſelf, that his very enemies would not tax him with covetouſneſs; he was ſlandered as though he had been too familiar with <hi>Olympias,</hi> but moſt impiouſly; both of them were the moſt mortified perſons the World afforded: and he avers, that if his body was ſeen, it would be a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient evidence to clear himſelf from ſo foul an imputation. He indeed was accuſed of Pride; indeed he was a perſon of a great Spirit, but free from ambition. He was very zealous for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Glory, and a ſevere hater of all vice; nothing could move him to favour impiety, which cauſed him by ſome evil perſons to be thought haughty and arrogant. They were both ſo far from being ambitious, that they both refuſed their Biſhopricks, and unwillingly accepted of them; and when ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to their Epiſcopal Sees, they managed their places with all imaginable humility and modeſty. I may truly ſay of them both, which <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſays of his Siſter <hi>Gorgonian,</hi> that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven was their Country; the City, of which they were deſirous, was the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> a City that is above, not ſeen by the eyes, but perceived by the underſtanding, and apprehended by Faith: In Heaven was their converſation; there they lived; to gain that, was their maineſt endeavour: they were genuine Chriſtians; what they preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:132826:51"/> and inculcated to others, that they practiſed; to ſhew therefore their contempt of any Worldly thing, among a thouſand paſſages I will pick out two, one of St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> the other of St. <hi>Chryſoſtom.</hi> St. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſhews the Heavenlineſs of his mind, in thoſe Divine thoughts of his, which we find in his Sermons on the 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5. 16, 17, 18. The deſign of which Sermon is to demonſtrate, that a genuine Chriſtian has reaſon continually to rejoyce. To perform which, he anſwers two objections: 1. That a joy proceeding from an accumulated felicity, which we partake of in this World, cannot be obtained; which objection he thus urges: Does our Law-giver enjoyn us impoſſible things? how is it poſſible always to rejoyce? no man can find the reaſon of that joy in his own power; thoſe things that raiſe a chearfulneſs, are without us; they are not within our own boſoms. The proſperity of the enjoyment of our Parents and Friends; the gaining and encreaſing our Revenues, a reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto health, a family proſperous and flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing. After this, he gives an account of other things neceſſary to humane felicity; but then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, that the complexion of thoſe things are not attainable. 2. The beſt of men are ſubject to the greateſt calamities. Shall I rejoyce, when tortured? when ſtretched upon a wheel? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Having elegantly given an account of thoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries that humane nature is obnoxious to; theſe things may ſeem to evince, by this Law impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things are enjoyned: to which he rejoyns in General, <hi>That the Apoſtle giving this command,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:132826:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> caſt his eye upon things future and Eternal; and thereby endeavoured to elevate the Souls of men:</hi> and that thoſe who queſtioned the poſſibility of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the Apoſtolical command, do roll them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about earth and fleſh, as Worms do about dung and filth. To theſe he returns, <hi>that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical command of rejoycing always is poſſible to thoſe, who have Christ living in them; to thoſe Souls, who are once inflamed with a deſire of their Maker, and are accuſtomed ſweetly to delight themſelves in thoſe beauties, which in him are to be found; receive comfort from thoſe very things which are afflicting of others:</hi> Towards the end of his Sermon, he ſhews, the ground of a Chriſtians Joy is an everlaſting felicity; for, ſaith he, <hi>if thy life is always intent upon God, the hope of a reward ſhall lighten the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of thy life: Art thou diſgraced? Oh, but look up to that Glory laid up in Heaven for them that are patient. Have you ſuſtained any damage or loſs in your Eſtate? Oh, but look with an intention of mind to thoſe Heavenly Riches, to thoſe treaſures which are laid up for them that live piouſly. Are you bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed your Country? but thou hast a Country, a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly</hi> Jeruſalem. <hi>Have you loſt your Children? I, but thou hast Angels, in the Quire of whom, thou ſhalt before the Throne of God be filled with an Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal joy: ſo therefore against theſe Temporal Calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, oppoſing thoſe good things expected, you ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your Soul from trouble and diſſolution. For to that undiſturbed mind, the Law of this Apoſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites us. Let not the ſplendour and gaiety of humane things work in our mind an exceſſive joy: neither let</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:132826:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>the dolorouſneſs and pain of them deject the Soul, caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it down from its height, and obſcuring its ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour; for he that is otherwiſe inſtructed concerning the affairs of this life, cannot poſſibly live calmly and undiſturbedly; which you ſhall ſucceſsfully attain, if you have this Commandment, exhorting you conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually to rejoyce, always dwelling with you. Let us therefore caſt away all the troubles of the fleſh; let us collect and embrace the delights of the Soul; and ſo aſcending above the ſenſe of things preſent, we may extend our underſtanding to the hope of Eternity; the very imagination of which thing is ſufficient to fill the Soul with joy, and to make the joy of Angels to be the inhabiter of our Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> upon <hi>Geneſis,</hi> Homily 35. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> after a great victory he had obtained over thoſe Kings, which had vanquiſhed the King of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and carried away <hi>Lot</hi> into captivity, was upon his victorious return met with by the King of <hi>Sodom,</hi> who deſired him to keep the ſpoils, and return the perſons; <hi>Abraham</hi> generouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, and Heroically ſaying, <hi>I have lift up my hand to the Lord, the moſt high God, the Poſſeſſor of Heaven and Earth; That I will not take from a thred even to a ſhoe-latchet, and that I will not take any thing that is thine, leſt thou ſhouldeſt ſay, I have made</hi> Abraham <hi>rich,</hi> Gen. 14. 22, 23. upon this, he thus diſcourſeth: <hi>Behold the incomparable vertue of this Patriarch; by the contempt of riches, and practice of humility, he ſhewed his Divine Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and by this means made his victory great and glorious. I paſſionately exhort that we may all imitate
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:132826:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> this Excellent Perſon; let us maintain an unbla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable life; let us not under the pretence of virtue, fall into the madneſs of vain-glory; nor of modeſty, into the contempt of pious actions; let us lay humility as the ſureſt foundation for a holy life; no actions are vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, which are not accompanied with humility: he that ſecurely hath laid this foundation, may raiſe the beautiful Temple of virtue as high as he pleaſes. Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility is the holy mans greateſt ſecurity; It is that wall which cannot be broken down, an invincible To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer. Our bountiful God, if he ſees us, as</hi> Abraham <hi>did, deſpiſe theſe preſent things, he will give us the enjoyment of future bleſſings. Let us deſpiſe the riches of this preſent World, that we be able to enjoy true and laſting pleaſures. Let us ſcorn this empty thing called vain-glory, that we partake of Honour which is true and Eternal. Let us laugh at the felicity of this preſent evil World, that unſpeakable felicities may make us happy for the future. Let us have cheap thoughts of thoſe things that are preſent, that our minds may be heightned by generous Paſſions, and our Souls inflamed with Heavenly deſires. If we be nailed to the things of this life, it is impoſſible that we ſhould be affected with Heavenly things. A Film and Rheum darkens the eye, and a love of this World clouds our Reaſon, and permits not to us the proſpect of Eternity: but he whoſe Soul is touched with the love of God, and heart wounded with arrows ſhot from Heaven, and in his breaſt is kindled a Heavenly fire, he with true and diſcerning eyes, ſees the glories of the future, and the vanities of this preſent life. Wilt thou, O Chriſtian, learn that wiſdom with which</hi>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:132826:53"/> 
               <hi>the Teacher of the World was endued? conſider how he clearly diſcovers, that whatſoever ſeems illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious in the World, is really nothing. Mark the Language that he uſeth,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 17. <hi>The things that are ſeen, ſay abundance of Riches, if you alledge Luſtre, Glory, and Majeſty, if Dominion, Power, if Empires, if Thrones and Crowns, all theſe things are ſeen, and are Temporal, their continuance is but ſhort, and the enjoyment of them but for a moment. If theſe things that are ſeen are but Temporal, what things, O bleſſed</hi> Paul, <hi>wouldſt thou have us to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue? He returns things not ſeen, things which cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral eyes cannot behold. If any one ſhall object, who is it that counſels us to neglect viſible, and purſue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible things? Heavenly</hi> Paul <hi>replies, the nature of the things, counſel and command; you ſee theſe things, you ſee them uncertain, and the continuance of them ſhort; but thoſe things which we cannot ſee, are Eternal, they know no end, nor admit of a Period.</hi> This he ſays was the ſubject of his continued La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and daily Sermons. So that that by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle pronounced concerning the Patriarchs, may be applyed to theſe great perſons: <hi>Heb. 11. 14. They that ſay ſuch things, declare plainly that they ſeek another Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſil</hi> having conſumed his body by vaſt labours, as a glorious Lamp that <note place="margin">Their deaths and Burials.</note> waſts it ſelf with its own fire, and goes out with the greateſt flame: So <hi>Baſil</hi> with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual faſting, in perpetual prayers, ſtudy and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, caſt himſelf into a perpetual ſickneſs, which cauſed him to ſtudy Phyſick. His inceſſant diſeaſe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:132826:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> made him a Phyſician, he ſcarce ever being in good health. Recovering out of a former diſeaſe, he was very much troubled, that being near the Haven, a contrary wind ſhould drive him into the Sea again. But after he had gloriouſly ruled the Church for 8 years and 2 months, <hi>Anno</hi> 378. he fell into his laſt ſickneſs, which was a violent Feaver: it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed not his Reaſon nor Religion; his Soul burnt with Divine ardours, and he caſt the flames of love to God in all his diſcourſes. When he could hardly ſpeak, and ready to give up the laſt Gaſp, he called for ſeveral of the Clergy and other Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſons, and gave them moſt prudent, moſt ſacred, moſt religious admonitions concerning both the guiding of their own lives, and ordering of the Church of God; and interrupting that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, his ſtrength being waſted, he breaks out into this Ejaculation, <hi>O Lord, into thy hands I commit my Spirit;</hi> and with that aſpiration his Soul flew to Heaven, and left the Body of <hi>Baſilius</hi> for the ſociety of Angels, expecting to receive it in the reſurrection of the Juſt. The news of his death being ſpread throughout the City, filled all with ſorrow and horrour. In him the very Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren thought they had loſt their Parents, Wives their Husbands, Parents their Children; the Glory, the Protection of the City they thought was gone: and his Funeral was celebrated by the confluence of all ſorts of people. The Deſarts were emptied of all their Religious perſons, the Country became unpeopled, <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> flocked to attend his Herſe: in ſo great a croud, many thronging to be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:132826:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> within the ſhadow of the Herſe, or to touch the Bier, periſhed; in ſo great a multitude, many were preſſed to death, as unwilling to ſurvive that great Perſon; being his funeral Victims, they would offer themſelves willingly a Sacrifice to this great Saint. The memory of him was ſo famous, that his very Geſtures, his Speech, his Garb, his Gate, every thing the moſt excellent Perſons endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to imitate, and they thought them admirable, who could expreſs in themſelves any thing of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilius.</hi> Alaſs! theſe were but faint repreſentations of his Virtues; as Ecchoes rebound but the laſt ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, ſo ſcarce any could expreſs the meaneſt of his Excellencies. His fame was ſo glorious, that he hath acquired the name of Great. <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> gained the ſame Title by their Arms and Victories, but he by Grace and the Triumphs of Religion. The univerſal teſtimony of the Church, hath canonized him for a Saint; his Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels grow out of his grave, and the glory of his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial ſhall never loſe its luſtre,</p>
            <p>The Emperours anger continuing ſtill againſt <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> prohibited the converſation of Letters with him, cauſed him to be removed from Place to Place, that it might be unknown where he was. Arriving at <hi>Caeſarea, Pharetrius</hi> Biſhop of that place, and ſucceſſor of <hi>Baſil,</hi> a man infinitely infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to his Predeceſſor, and of a different humour, denied him Lodgings in the City, prohibited a Religious Lady that lived 5 miles diſtant from <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarea,</hi> to entertain him. The famous Biſhop gave the foreign Communion to Strangers, Pagans,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:132826:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> to Hereticks; but how differently contrary is <hi>Pharetrius,</hi> who permits not an entertainment to <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> the moſt glorious Prelate of the World. After one years reſt and civil uſage at <hi>Cucuſum,</hi> he was hurried to <hi>Petiuntum;</hi> the Souldiers ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving received a ſpecial command from the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, that they ſhould not permit him any quiet, nor ſuffer his decayed body to receive any refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by eaſe; in violent ſtorms he ſhould have no ſhelter, in great heats he ſhould not have the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the ſhades, but be carried from place to place. Yet in all theſe troubles, his mind was elevated, always comforting diſconſolate Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. Thus he, whilſt he was gloriouſly fighting in the Front of the Battle, encouraged the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in the Rear. Carried to <hi>Comanum,</hi> he, as the cuſtoms of holy men were to enter the Church, goes to the Temple of <hi>Baſiliſcus</hi> to pray; after which his Feaver increaſing, worn with labours, waſted by travels, in holy prayers and Ejacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he gives up the Ghoſt, <hi>Anno</hi> 407. having ſat in the See 9 years 7 months and 8 days. He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd a Temple to pray, immediately before he was to enter into that Temple, where the Lamb is the light thereof. A period is put to the Travels of this Pilgrim, his baniſhment finds an end; now he enters into the City of God, that new <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and is in that place where there remains a reſt for the Servants of God. The news of his death flying into <hi>Armenia,</hi> and the adjacent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, they were all ſtruck with an exceſſive grief: the Inhabitants forſook their Country, to celebrate
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:132826:55"/> the Funeral of this great Perſon. He was carried to the grave upon the ſhoulders of the moſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſons, people of divers Nations being at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants of that ſolemnity. Divers Languages conſpired in one praiſe; all tongues ſent up the ſame Halelujahs. With Prayers, Pſalmodies, with Hymns, the people of all eſtates and conditions, &amp; of various Countries celebrated that ſad ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: and being carried to the Church of St. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliſcus,</hi> he was there interred. He lived with great Fame; his enemies could never obſcure, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his glory; his Memorial can never be buried in oblivion. His enemies raced his name out of the ſacred <hi>Dipticks,</hi> but it will always remain in the Book of life. The conſent of the univerſal Church hath reckoned him amongſt the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of Saints. A very conſiderable part of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> ſeparated from the Church, and had their conventions under ſome Biſhops, the favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of <hi>Chryſostom.</hi> Theſe were called <hi>Joannites,</hi> againſt whom the Emperour made ſevere Edicts, for they would not be forced to communicate at the Altar, whoſe <hi>Dipticks</hi> admitted not the name of <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> and by reaſon of that great injury done to this famous Biſhop and Saint, the whole Weſtern Church refuſed a communion with the <hi>Constantinopolitan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Proclus,</hi> formerly a Deacon under <hi>Chryſostom,</hi> was advanced to the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople.</hi> He prevailed upon that moſt excellent and Religious Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the younger, the Son of <hi>Arcadius,</hi> that the body of <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:132826:55"/> ſhould be tranſlated from <hi>Comanum</hi> to <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> which was performed 38 years after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe. The Corps were received with the higheſt joy, mixed with infinite ſhame and ſorrow; with the extreameſt ſhame and ſorrow, that ſo great a Prelate, ſo admirable a Preacher, ſo holy a man, Chriſtians ſhould baniſh into the remoteſt parts of the World. What infinite ſorrow, to conceive that a Chriſtian City ſhould be deprived of ſo glorious a Perſon, and his death to be haſtened by the hands of Chriſtians, whoſe life deſerved to be prolonged by all poſſible care and induſtry. Yet what joy, to ſee the Empire changed, the City all attending the Ship that brought the Corps of their baniſhed Archbiſhop. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> himſelf, an Emperour compoſed with valour, and goodneſs; a perſon of the greateſt courage, and ſweeteſt tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in the World, being the chief Mourner. And thus <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> is carried with all imaginable pomp, and with all the ſacred ſolemnities, to the Church of St. <hi>Sophia,</hi> his holy name is re-inſerted into the Sacred <hi>Dipticks;</hi> and in the grave of <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> all contentions were buried, the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern and Weſtern Churches reconciled, no private conventions maintained, but all met in the unity of the Spirit, and bond of peace. The works of this perſon are many and incomparable; his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors after they came from Church would uſually cry, O Golden Mouth! While he lived, and two ages at leaſt after his death, he was known by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon diſcourſe and writing by the name of <hi>John,</hi> but afterwards the glory of his writings gave him the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:132826:56"/> cognomen of <hi>Chryſoſtom:</hi> and indeed nothing can ſhine in greater luſtre, then he in the excellency of Eloquence, piety and induſtry. Thus theſe two great perſons, as the <hi>Phoenix</hi> having made a Neſt, which is her Funeral Pile, of the odoriferous bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which the Aromatick Trees of <hi>Arabia</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, by an agitation of the Air through the nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble motion of her wings, cauſeth the <hi>Solar</hi> Beams to ſet it on fire, which being kindled, ſhe lays her ſelf quietly in thoſe flames, and there with great content expires; knowing that of thoſe aſhes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother more Juvenile and ſprightly <hi>Phoenix</hi> ſhall ariſe: ſo theſe great perſons, having prepared for themſelves by their actions (more fragrant and ſweet then the odours of the Eaſt) an Eternal Monument, are laid in the grave in the ſweeteſt repoſe; knowing that out of their aſhes there ſhall ariſe thoſe Bodies (which are in this World em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balmed with the perfumes of a great Fame, and the odours of glorious actions) that ſhall be inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with light and immortality.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:132826:56"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
